<book botname="Virtual Dan" ambig="0.7" thresh="1.5">
  <leadtopics>
    where howhi weather route howlong cuz risks food camp4 noridge 
    cost mandm rhein clothing sleepbag tent skills crowd mybio toilet 
    carry oxy wash praise yes seizure eastrong tibet yaks sherpas 
    headwall camp5 norman camp6 sumday frostbite kathmandu water abc 
    mallory aval health typday dzone basecamp rongmon acclim yakdriver
    yeti gear bye imfine confused rudedude story hi haha whereami hafe
    goodbye 
  </leadtopics>
  <noisewords>
    a about all also am an and any are aren't as at be been before 
    but by can could did do does don't ever Everest for from go 
    going had happens has have he her here his how i if in into is 
    isn't it it's its Dan kind like me much must my my need now of 
    off often oh on or our said same say she tell that the their 
    there therefore these they this those through to too until up 
    want was we were what when where which while who why will with 
    would you your 
  </noisewords>
  <noise phrase="Hi Dan"/>
  <noise phrase="Hi Virtual Dan"/>
  <noise phrase="tell me"/>
  <noise phrase="tell me about"/>
  <keywords>
    defecate urinate
    1 2 3 4 5 6 advanced afraid avalanche axe bag bags base basecamp 
    bite bodies buddhist calls camp close col cold cost country 
    crampons crap crowded danger dangerous dead dehydrated die died 
    drink drinking dump east equipment expensive experience five 
    food four frost great headwall heavy high Hillary ice II III 
    Irvine IV kathmandu Mallory monastery nepal north ok okay one 
    oxygen packs qualifications rescue rescues ridge risky rongbuk 
    routing scared shit sick sickness six sleep sleeping sponsor 
    stories story temples tent tents thank thanks three toilet trash 
    two understand V VI view warm water wearing yes yeti yourself 
  </keywords>
  <key phrase="because it's there"/>
 
  <question topic="story">Tell me a story</question>
  <question topic="story">Do you have any stories to tell?</question>
  <answer topic="story" repeat="yes" offer="no" 
  about="an Everest story">
    <btw topic="highchair">
      Well, if all this stuff has been a bit too serious so far, maybe
      this will help. 
      <p/>
      <include answer="highchair"/> 
      <else>
        <btw topic="seizure">
          Here's a tale that might give you an idea of the medical and
          logistical problems up here. Planning is good, but often, on
          Everest, one is called upon to react, instead of just act. 
          <p/>
          <include answer="seizure"/> 
          <else>
            <btw topic="norman">
              Here is a story of someone whose wish may have been 
              granted. 
              <p/>
              <include answer="norman"/> 
              <else>
                <btw topic="aval">
                  This is a story about <i>luck</i> and <i>skill</i> 
                  ... both come highly recommended. 
                  <p/>
                  <include answer="aval"/> 
                  <else>
                    <btw topic="mandm">
                      This is a story about another Mike and Mark... 
                      <p/>
                      <include answer="mandm"/> 
                      <else>
                        Phew! I've run out of stories to tell. But you
                        can still ask me about other things... like 
                        the example topics, below. 
                      </else>
                    </btw>
                  </else>
                </btw>
              </else>
            </btw>
          </else>
        </btw>
      </else>
    </btw>
  </answer>
  <key phrase="how high"/>
 
  <question topic="howhi">How high are you?</question>
  <question topic="howhi">How high is Everest?</question>
  <question topic="howhi">How high is the summit</question>
  <question topic="howhi">How high is Mount Everest?</question>
  <question topic="howhi">
    what is the height of Mt. Everest?
  </question>
  <question topic="howhi">What is your altitude?</question>
  <question topic="howhi">altitude</question>
  <question topic="howhi">Everest's height</question>
  <answer topic="howhi" about="the height of Everest" 
  next="where,route,sumday">
    Here are a few altitudes to put things into perspective. 
    <table border="1" cellpadding="5" align="center">
      <tr>
        <td align="right">
          Feet 
        </td>
        <td align="left">
          What 
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="right">
          11,600 
        </td>
        <td align="left">
          Mt. Fuji, Japan 
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="right">
          12,000 
        </td>
        <td align="left">
          Pilots of private planes use oxygen 
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="right">
          14,700 
        </td>
        <td align="left">
          The Matterhorn 
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="right">
          17,000 
        </td>
        <td align="left">
          Everest Base Camp 
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="right">
          19,300 
        </td>
        <td align="left">
          Kilimanjaro (highest point in Africa) 
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="right">
          20,000 
        </td>
        <td align="left">
          You would suffocate if you went directly to this altitude 
          without acclimatizing. 
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="right">
          20,320 
        </td>
        <td align="left">
          McKinley (highest point in North America) 
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="right">
          21,500 
        </td>
        <td align="left">
          Everest Advanced Base Camp (ABC) 
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="right">
          23,000 
        </td>
        <td align="left">
          Aconcagua (highest point in South America) <br/> Everest 
          Camp 4 (North Col) 
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="right">
          27,500 
        </td>
        <td align="left">
          Everest Camp 6, "the highest mountain camp in the world" 
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="right">
          29,035 
        </td>
        <td align="left">
          Everest Summit (highest point I can see from here!) 
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <p/>
    Since I am at the North Col (23,000 feet), you can see that I am 
    pretty well at the halfway point, altitude wise, between Base Camp
    (17,000 feet) and the summit (just over 29,000 feet). 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="eastrong">Where is Camp 1?</question>
  <question topic="eastrong">How high is Camp 1?</question>
  <question topic="eastrong">East Rongbuk Glacier</question>
  <question topic="eastrong">
    Tell me about the first part of the route.
  </question>
  <question topic="eastrong">
    What is it like crossing the glacier?
  </question>
  <answer topic="eastrong" about="the East Rongbuk Glacier" 
  next="yaks,znabc,zpbase,headwall">
    <img src="evm098.jpg" align="right"/>
    The route from 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp</a>
    leads up the East Rongbuk Glacier... which we follow for 12 miles 
    (20 kilometers) to 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$abc">Advanced Base Camp</a>
    at the base of the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$headwall">headwall.</a>
    <p/>
    Here's the view at the start of that journey, a little way up the 
    glacier from Base Camp. You can see the ice peeking through the 
    moraine. That symmetrical icy peak is Pumori. 
    <p/>
    Camp 1 and Camp 2 sit on the glacier. They are basically outposts 
    for moving supplies. Early on in the expedition, we did 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$carry">carries</a>
    to these camps to help us 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$acclim">acclimatize</a>
    to the altitude. 
    <p/>
    <br clear="all"/> 
    <img src="evm150.jpg" align="right"/>
    Much of the glacier consists of house sized boulders, or giant 
    blocks of ice. But in some places, small gravel and rocks in the 
    glacial ice have accumulated into a <i>medial moraine,</i> which 
    has melted into the glacial ice to form a highway, with icy 
    glacial walls on both sides. 
    <p/>
    Needless to say, this highway provided a welcome change from the 
    ice blocks or giant boulders. We loved it. So did the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$yaks">yaks.</a>
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="tibet">Tell me about Tibet</question>
  <question topic="tibet">What is Tibet like?</question>
  <answer topic="tibet" about="Tibet" 
  next="znoturd,rongmon,sherpas,yaks,basecamp">
    <img src="evs092.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evs145.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evs131.jpg" align="right"/>
    We came through a number of Tibetan villages on the way to Base 
    Camp. Tibet is China's Wild, Wild West... with brave but clueless 
    city slickers from the East coming out here for multi year 
    assignments to tame the frontier and subdue the natives. 
    <p/>
    <br clear="all"/> 
    <img src="evm074.jpg" align="right"/>
    Here is a typical Tibetan home... with fuel providing a decorative
    motif. That's firewood on the roof. And in case you were 
    wondering, why <i>yes,</i> those <i>are</i> yak turds mushed to 
    the wall to dry. 
    <p/>
    Dry turds are good fuel, too, and in a place where wood is so 
    rare, you do what ya gotta do. Waste not, want not... 
    <p/>
    Welcome to the Turd World. Care to come in and warm yourself by 
    the fire? 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="znoturd" offer="no" synonym="no">
    Well, I didn't think you would. 
    <btw topic="rongmon">
      But maybe I could tell you about another piece of Tibet. 
      <p/>
      <include answer="rongmon"/> 
      <else>
        <btw topic="yaks">
          But you should know that yaks have some redeeming 
          attributes. 
          <p/>
          <include answer="yaks"/> 
        </btw>
      </else>
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="yaks">Did you use yaks?</question>
  <question topic="yaks">What are yaks like?</question>
  <question topic="yaks">How many yak loads did you have?</question>
  <question topic="yaks">Tell me about yaks</question>
  <question topic="yaks">How high did the yaks go?</question>
  <answer topic="yaks" about="yaks" 
  next="zyakdriver,tibet,sherpas,basecamp,abc">
    <img src="evm100.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evm112.jpg" align="right"/>
    Here on the North Side were able to use yaks all the way to 
    advanced base... and a good thing, too, because 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$abc">Advanced Base Camp</a>
    (also known as ABC) isn't something you'd want to carry on your 
    back. It took a hundred yak loads to set up ABC... I'd hate to 
    think how many climber loads that would have been. 
    <p/>
    Most people haven't seen yaks. But then, most people haven't been 
    above 11,000 feet, and below that, there are bacteria which the 
    yaks' pathetic immune system can't handle. 
    <p/>
    Yaks look pretty fearsome, but in fact they're pretty calm and 
    lethargic. Like a rusty machine, they grind to a halt when not 
    being prodded forward. 
    <p/>
    <btw topic="yakdriver">
      Tibetan 
      <a href="teacher?query=$$yakdriver">yak drivers</a>
      provide that prodding. They also provide a bit of excitement on 
      the glacier. 
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="why">why?</question>
  <question topic="why">what?</question>
  <question topic="why">oh?</question>
  <question topic="why">huh?</question>
  <question topic="why">what do you mean</question>
  <question topic="why">how so</question>
  <question topic="why">in what way</question>
  <answer topic="why" offer="no">
    How would I know? 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="zyakdriver" synonym="why" about="yak drivers">
    <include answer="yakdriver"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="yakdriver">What kind of excitement</question>
  <question topic="yakdriver">excitement?</question>
  <question topic="yakdriver">yak drivers</question>
  <answer topic="yakdriver" about="yak drivers" 
  next="yaks,eastrong,abc,tibet,rongmon,headwall">
    <img src="evm239.jpg" align="right"/>
    Yak drivers are cut from different cloth than their 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$sherpas">sherpa</a>
    brethren. You see, yak drivers are out to make a buck. And, yak 
    drivers have a propensity to pilfer... 
    <p/>
    One of the things they like to steal is rope. And, one of the 
    things that holds your Camp 1 and Camp 2 tents to this Earth are, 
    coincidentally, also rope. 
    <p/>
    This unfortunate coincidence meant that, on more than one 
    occasion, we found ourselves scouring nearby glaciers for tents 
    that had blown away. Not funny if those tents contain the only 
    food, fuel, and sleeping bags for miles around. 
    <p/>
    If you leave anything outside the tent, consider it subject to 
    unscheduled removal. And, if you didn't put a padlock on your tent
    zipper, all that stuff is fair game, too. 
    <p/>
    I find it somewhat whimsical that, at 20,000 feet on the north 
    side of Everest, you have to lock your doors at night. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="sherpas">Tell me about the Sherpas</question>
  <question topic="sherpas">what are sherpas?</question>
  <answer topic="sherpas" about="sherpas" 
  next="basecamp,kathmandu,yaks,tibet,rongmon">
    <img src="evm253.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evm089.jpg" align="right"/>
    Our expedition is supported by a dozen Sherpas. The Sherpa people,
    originating in the Khumbu region of Nepal, are wonderful. Self 
    motivated, yet selfless. Willing to contribute unquestioningly 
    under the most difficult circumstances. 
    <p/>
    Tough, yet happy. 
    <p/>
    So unlike us. 
    <p/>
    Their duties varied. Many helped establish camps, and carry loads 
    to them. Others tended camp. Others cooked. 
    <p/>
    There's a big cultural gap, complicated further by a language gap.
    Several climbers made a point of socializing with the Sherpas, but
    in many cases the the Sherpas participated out of deference. 
    Perhaps the most successful social interactions involved working 
    together. 
  </answer>
  <key phrase="ice climbing"/>
 
  <question topic="headwall">Is there a lot of ice climbing</question>
  <question topic="headwall">What is the steepest part</question>
  <question topic="headwall">What is the headwall like?</question>
  <question topic="headwall">Where do you go after ABC?</question>
  <answer topic="headwall" about="the headwall" 
  next="zncamp4,noridge,camp5,zpabc,eastrong">
    <img src="evm035.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evm080.jpg" align="right"/>
    At the head of the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$eastrong">East Rongbuk Glacier</a>
    lies a 1500 foot headwall. Below it is 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$abc">Advanced Base Camp,</a>
    and above it... well, it's the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$camp4">North Col</a>
    where I am "chilling out" now. 
    <p/>
    We put in fixed lines up the headwall to make it easier for the 
    team to haul loads up here to the Col. 
    <p/>
    There's lots of ice here... and lots of history. One of the early 
    attempts to climb Everest ended abruptly when an 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$aval">avalanche</a>
    killed 7 sherpas here in 1922, causing many to question why people
    wanted to to climb the mountain. The moving ice means that every 
    year this headwall presents a different challenge to climbers... 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="rprev">Was it hard to get there?</question>
  <question topic="rprev">How did you get there?</question>
  <question topic="rprev">
    It must have been difficult to get there.
  </question>
  <answer topic="rprev" about="how to get there" offer="no">
    This should never occur... we only use this as a synonym 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="rnext">What happens next?</question>
  <question topic="rnext">Then what?</question>
  <question topic="rnext">Then where?</question>
  <question topic="rnext">Then where do you go</question>
  <question topic="rnext">and after that</question>
  <question topic="rnext">and then?</question>
  <question topic="rnext">where do you go after that</question>
  <question topic="rnext">Where do you go from here?</question>
  <question topic="rnext">What will you do next?</question>
  <answer topic="rnext" about="what I do next" offer="no">
    This should never occur... we only use this as a synonym 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="noridge">What happens tomorrow?</question>
  <question topic="noridge">North Ridge</question>
  <answer topic="noridge" about="the North Ridge" 
  next="zncamp5,camp6,sumday,zpcamp4,headwall,zblowaway">
    <img src="evm125.jpg" align="right"/>
    Tomorrow we head up the North Ridge, making our way to 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$camp5">Camp 5.</a>
    <p/>
    As you can see, it's a windwept, snow covered ridge, pretty 
    inhospitable a few weeks ago because of the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$weather">jet stream.</a>
    The Ridge tends to be a windy place anyway, since the North Face 
    tends to funnel the wind. 
    <p/>
    On my first carry I used a face mask on the Ridge because the 
    conditions were too harsh for exposed flesh. One of the Sherpas 
    now has semicircles of frostbite under his eyes, where his 
    facemask and goggles didn't quite seal! 
    <p/>
    We'll be climbing 2,000 feet higher, and I think we'll start using
    <a href="teacher?query=$$oxy">oxygen</a>
    towards the top of the ridge. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="zblowaway">Can you be blown off?</question>
  <question topic="zblowaway">
    Can't you get blown off the ridge
  </question>
  <answer topic="zblowaway" offer="no" about="getting 'blown away'" 
  next="zbahi,zncamp5,zpcamp4,route,dzone">
    <img src="evm084.jpg" align="right"/>
    Well, I suppose it's windy enough to get blown off. 
    <p/>
    I think you'd probably need a 200MPH gust for that... 100MPH 
    probably knocks you down, but doesn't give you enough lift for 
    takeoff. 
    <p/>
    Earlier on I ventured out on the North Ridge with an anemometer 
    when we were trying to gauge the jet stream... they also timed the
    winds from basecamp, timing clouds zipping past landmarks on the 
    North Face, estimating the wind at 100MPH. 
    <p/>
    Under those conditions, I felt pretty unstable... I could not get 
    a decent anemometer reading... but I didn't feel I was about to 
    take off. 
    <p/>
    Of course, lots of things smaller than people were getting 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$highchair">blown away.</a>
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="zbahi">like what?</question>
  <answer topic="zbahi" synonym="why" offer="no">
    The winds of Everest had me scared sh*tless... read on. 
    <p/>
    <include answer="highchair"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="camp5">when do you go to Camp 5?</question>
  <question topic="camp5">Tell me about camp 5</question>
  <question topic="camp5">How high is Camp 5?</question>
  <question topic="camp5">Camp five</question>
  <question topic="camp5">Camp V</question>
  <answer topic="camp5" about="Camp 5" 
  next="zncamp6,sumday,zpnoridge,oxy,camp4,route,dzone,acclim">
    <img src="evm046.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evm198.jpg" align="right"/>
    Camp 5 is placed amid a jumble of rocks at the top of the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$noridge">North Ridge</a>
    Maybe the best way of finding it is with a metal detector. There 
    are hundreds of empty 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$oxy">oxygen</a>
    bottles up there. It's not a place where you can expect to get 
    much sleep... exposed to the wind, with no real flat spot in 
    sight. 
    <p/>
    Our first crack at establishing Camp 5 wasn't very successful. The
    storms of April returned, and flattened the tents. Remarkable, 
    given that these tents were constructed with special strength 
    tubing to withstand 100 MPH winds. Makes you wonder... but not 
    enough to want to have been there. 
    <p/>
    At 25,500 feet, this camp places us in the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$dzone">death zone,</a>
    so named because of the debilitating effects of this altitude. 
    After spending the night at this garden spot, we'll move on to 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$camp6">Camp 6.</a>
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="camp6">Tell me about camp 6</question>
  <question topic="camp6">Where is camp six?</question>
  <question topic="camp6">Camp VI</question>
  <answer topic="camp6" about="Camp 6" 
  next="znsumday,zpcamp5,oxy,route,dzone,acclim">
    <img src="evm193.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evm036.jpg" align="right"/>
    We strike out across the North Face across mixed snow and rock to 
    reach Camp 6, our highest camp. It's not exactly an inviting 
    location... unsheltered, far from level. 
    <p/>
    Camp 6 lies in the Yellow Band, so named because of the underlying
    rock layer, not because of this tent. 
    <p/>
    From here, after a short and difficult sleep, we'll head for 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$sumday">the summit.</a>
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="sumday">What is the hardest part?</question>
  <question topic="sumday">most difficult obstacle?</question>
  <question topic="sumday">Tell me about Summit Day</question>
  <question topic="sumday">What is summit day like?</question>
  <answer topic="sumday" about="Summit Day" 
  next="cuz,zpcamp6,oxy,dzone,route,acclim">
    <img src="evm185.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evm189.jpg" align="right"/>
    The hardest part about climbing Everest is the summit day. The 
    most difficult and exposed climbing of the Expedition occur on 
    that day, at a point when you are least able to cope: you're at a 
    low point in strength, stamina, and mental agility. 
    <p/>
    On this side of the mountain, there are a lot of downward sloping 
    slabs of rock on the upper mountain... and 9,000 feet of the North
    Face waiting below you for you to make your first, and last, 
    mistake. 
    <p/>
    I've spent a lifetime preparing for that day... but I know that 
    when it comes, it will be at the edge of my ability... I'll be 
    depending on luck, as well as preparation. 
    <p/>
    From 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$camp6">Camp 6</a>
    we will rise at midnight for a 2AM start up to the summit, which 
    we should reach well before noon. 
    <p/>
    That will give us time to descend the way we came, straight past 
    Camp 6, and on to 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$camp5">Camp 5</a>
    getting out of the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$dzone">death zone</a>
    as soon as we possibly can. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="oxy">How long does an oxygen tank last?</question>
  <question topic="oxy">
    What kind of oxygen equipment do you use?
  </question>
  <question topic="oxy">Are you using oxygen?</question>
  <question topic="oxy">How long can you use oxygen?</question>
  <answer topic="oxy" about="using oxygen" 
  next="acclim,health,dzone,route,food">
    <img src="maltanks.jpg" align="right"/>
    We'll be using oxygen above about 25,000 feet, using Russian Army 
    surplus oxygen gear. So I guess this gear is finally seeing active
    service in a different kind of "cold war". 
    <p/>
    Oxygen and Everest have had a long association. 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$mallory">Mallory and Irvine</a>
    used oxygen during their fateful attempt in June, 1924. This photo
    was taken here, at the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$camp4">North Col.</a>
    <p/>
    Using oxygen causes a lot of philosophical discussion amongst 
    climbers. Some feel that using oxygen is unfair. I suppose I take 
    a pragmatic view, seeing oxygen as an important tool. Few people 
    would argue that climbing Everest with crampons or down clothing 
    is "unfair". I don't see oxygen as being any different. Others 
    disagree with me rather violently. 
    <p/>
    <img src="evm075.jpg" align="right"/>
    You shouldn't get the idea that climbing on oxygen makes your body
    perform as if you're at sea level or something. At the upper end 
    of the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$noridge">North Ridge,</a>
    I tried an experiment. 
    <p/>
    Going up a steep part of the ridge, I found I was taking one step 
    for every ten breaths. If you can visualize that, you have an idea
    of what slow going it was. I tried to pick up the pace, and 
    sustain eight breaths per step... I found I couldn't do it. 
    <p/>
    Now, trying it on oxygen... five breaths per step! Nirvana! Still 
    an order of magnitude slower than sea level... but a major 
    improvement, and a decisive one high on the mountain. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="frostbite">
    What sort of danger is there from frost bite?
  </question>
  <question topic="frostbite">How does frostbite happen?</question>
  <answer topic="frostbite" about="frostbite" 
  next="oxy,dzone,weather,acclim">
    <img src="evm179.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evm216.jpg" align="right"/>
    Frostbite is what happens when the flesh freezes. 
    <p/>
    It happens pretty often up here. Given the altitude, blood 
    circulation isn't what it should be, so extremities such as 
    Gordy's hands or Mark's feet aren't kept warm the way they ought 
    to be. 
    <p/>
    The result is painful and easily infected. It's good practice to 
    soak the affected area in antibiotics... which isn't always 
    practical, especially in places where you get frostbite to begin 
    with. 
    <p/>
    Depending on the severity, frostbitten areas may heal, but they 
    may have to be amputated. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="kathmandu">Did you see Kathmandu?</question>
  <question topic="kathmandu">Tell me about Nepal</question>
  <answer topic="kathmandu" about="Kathmandu" 
  next="tibet,sherpas,rongmon,yaks,basecamp">
    <img src="evm008.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evm034.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evm300.jpg" align="right"/>
    Some of us approached Everest from Nepal, and some from China. I 
    came in with the trucks of gear we brought in from Nepal, starting
    in Kathmandu. 
    <p/>
    Prepare to be pestered in Kathmandu. You're obviously an outsider.
    Folks will continuously offer to sell you hashish, or offer to 
    change money on the black market. 
    <p/>
    It's an interesting place to wander around... shops, street 
    vendors, temples, and interesting people. You'll find aspects of 
    both Hindu and Buddhist religions. There is an exiled 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$tibet">Tibetan</a>
    community there. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="water">Where did you get water?</question>
  <question topic="water">Dehydration</question>
  <question topic="water">What do you drink</question>
  <question topic="water">What are you drinking</question>
  <answer topic="water" about="water on the mountain" 
  next="food,clothing,zleak,oxy,gear,wash">
    People are often surprised to hear what an important role <i>water
    </i> plays on the upper mountain. 
    <p/>
    You lose liquid much faster up here... the air is closer to vacuum
    than it is to the "air" we know at sea level; lots of liquid is 
    lost through the simple act of breathing. And the body doesn't do 
    a very good job of using the liquid it's given at this altitude. 
    Furthermore, the body doesn't help you you by reminding you, 
    through thirst, of its needs... so unless you make a conscious 
    effort, you'll end up dehydrated. 
    <p/>
    The risks are many. Dehydration can lead to exhaustion, stokes, 
    pulmonary or cerebral edema... a variety of potentially lethal 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$health">health problems.</a>
    I aim to drink 4 liters (quarts) of water a day. I keep track of 
    it, and make plans around it. 
    <p/>
    An important part of the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$typday">daily routine</a>
    revolves around water. After all, up here we need to melt snow to 
    get water. It's a time consuming chore. At each camp, we have a 
    designated "clean snow" area... we go out there, fill up a big 
    plastic garbage bag, bring it back into the tent, melt it down, 
    and fill water bottles. It's annoying how much snow you need. 
    <p/>
    And then, those water bottles would just freeze again unless you 
    take precautions. Water bottles go into your sleeping bag at 
    night... 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="zleak">What happens if the bottles leak?</question>
  <question topic="zleak">What if they leak?</question>
  <answer topic="zleak" about="leaking water bottles">
    If water bottles leak, you're in trouble! This happened to a 
    friend... not here on Everest, but on another expedition... the 
    whole foot of his sleeping bag froze solid. You can imagine this 
    is not an easy problem to solve. You can't just hang out a 
    sleeping bag to dry under these conditions! And it's not just an 
    inconvenience. The sleeping bag is an important part of living and
    staying warm up here. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="sleepbag">
    Tell me about your sleeping bag
  </question>
  <question topic="sleepbag">
    What kind of sleeping bag do you have
  </question>
  <question topic="sleepbag">sleeping bag</question>
  <answer topic="sleepbag" about="sleeping bags" 
  next="clothing,gear,tent">
    Our sleeping bags up here, as you can imagine, are the warmest you
    can find in the world... not only because it's cold here, but also
    because, at this altitude, the body is inefficient at keeping 
    itself warm and needs all the help it can get. 
    <p/>
    The heart of a good sleeping bag is insulation, and ours are all 
    insulated with goose down. There are lots of artificial fills out 
    there... they are generally very good, and better than goose down 
    in wet conditions... but so far no artificial insulation has 
    matched down's insulating power per unit weight. I tried an 
    artificial bag on Shishapangma a few years back... and had a water
    bottle freeze <i>inside the bag...</i> so I sold that bag when I 
    got back to 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$kathmandu">Kathmandu!</a>
    <p/>
    They're all mummy bags up here... enclosing your head as well as 
    your body. 
    <p/>
    Sleeping bags in upper camps are group resources... once a bag is 
    up there, it stays there for the next guy. There's enough stuff to
    carry that we can't afford to lug bags up and down the mountain 
    with each carry. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="tent">What kind of tents do you use</question>
  <question topic="tent">Tell me about your tent.</question>
  <answer topic="tent" about="tents">
    <img src="evm225.jpg" align="right"/>
    We tend to use internal frame dome tents up here... they are 
    strong and light. 
    <p/>
    Some of the tents we have for the upper mountain are experimental 
    units provided by a major tent manufacturer... with oversized 
    poles to take high winds. These tents have been tested under 
    controlled conditions with winds over 100MPH. 
    <p/>
    Strength is not enough... tents can get blown off as complete 
    units! Especially on the upper mountain, we go to extremes to 
    "nail down" the tents. 
    <p/>
    These tents here at 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$camp4">Camp 4</a>
    are secured with nets over the top, built of tubular nylon 
    (breaking strength measured in tons). These are pegged into the 
    ice with 3 foot metal pickets. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="acclim">
    How did you adapt to the altitude?
  </question>
  <question topic="acclim">Is it difficult to breathe?</question>
  <question topic="acclim">How thin was the air?</question>
  <question topic="acclim">Is breathing difficult?</question>
  <question topic="acclim">Did you get altitude sickness?</question>
  <question topic="acclim">Was it hard to breathe up there?</question>
  <answer topic="acclim" about="acclimatizing to altitude" 
  next="oxy,dzone,health,zseiz,water,food">
    <img src="evm018.jpg" align="right"/>
    If you were suddenly transported to 20,000 feet from sea level, 
    you'd die of suffocation. And yet, I'm at 23,000 feet now. Why 
    don't I suffocate? 
    <p/>
    Because I'm <i>acclimatized...</i> that is, my body has gradually 
    adapted to the thinner air over a period of weeks. Early in the 
    expedition, we go through a systematic process of incrementally 
    exposing our bodies to altitude... "carry high, sleep low"... as 
    we move equipment up from lower camps. This pattern exposes our 
    body to altitude, and then lets it recover (and rest) at night. 
    <p/>
    Gradually, our body adapts, and we find that our strength and 
    stamina lets us go farther, faster. 
    <p/>
    When altitude related 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$health">health problems</a>
    <i>do</i> strike, there is always an answer: Go down! Or, if you 
    have one of these inflatable iron lung jobbies (known as a "Gamow 
    Bag"), like we did at base camp, you can climb in here, get 
    somebody to pump you up, and simulate a short visit to sea level. 
    (Beach views not included.) 
    <btw topic="seizure">
      <p/>
      Of course, sometimes descending 
      <a href="teacher?query=$$seizure">isn't as easy as it sounds. 
      </a>
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="zseiz" about="a crisis at high altitude" 
  synonym="why">
    Here's an example of what can happen when altitude related medical
    problems occur where you most expect them... on the upper 
    mountain. 
    <p/>
    <include answer="seizure"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="seizure">Any exciting rescues?</question>
  <answer topic="seizure" about="a close call at 21,500 feet" 
  next="oxy,acclim,dzone,health,water,food">
    <img src="evm250.jpg" align="right"/>
    Imagine you're at 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$abc">Advanced Base Camp,</a>
    at around 21,500 feet. It's quite common for the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$sherpas">Sherpas</a>
    there to collect in one side of the mess tent, chattering to each 
    other in their native tongue, while the climbers do much the same 
    on the other side of the tent. There's relatively little contact 
    across that boundary; the language gap and culture gap was too 
    wide. 
    <p/>
    This particular evening was no different. Phinzo, over in the 
    Sherpa corner, was making a dramatic point. He raised his arm in a
    gesture, and froze. 
    <p/>
    At sea level, blood is about 40% solid material. At altitude, it 
    approaches 70%. 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$health">Things happen.</a>
    Blood clots... embolisms... and, in Phinzo's case, a stroke... a 
    blockage in blood flow in the brain. He suffered through several 
    <i>gran mal</i> seizures... thrashing wildly. Luckily, there was a
    doctor there... I think she was Austrian, part of a German team 
    which was also established at ABC. It was an all-out battle to 
    keep Phinzo alive. He had to be physically restrained... recurrent
    seizures... various drugs were administered... decadron, I 
    think... IV drip to thin down the blood... 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$oxy">oxygen</a>
    masks. Not a whole lot of sleep was had that night. His condition 
    was not stable. He had to come down. More easily said than done...
    the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$eastrong">East Rongbuk Glacier</a>
    is an obstacle course for a <i>healthy</i> person... how to get 
    somebody down on a stretcher...? 
    <p/>
    I was at 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp</a>
    for the the 7AM radio call, when we got the news that a team, 
    comprised of Americans, Sherpas, Canadians, Germans, others... 
    were already well underway bringing Phinzo down the glacier. A 
    makeshift stretcher... 15 miles of rugged terrain. 6-8 people per 
    shift. 5 minutes at a shift. Juggling to maintain IV and oxygen. 
    <p/>
    His condition remained critical for the duration. At one point, 
    the oxygen stopped... changing tanks, I think. Another seizure. By
    the time it was over, some 30 people were involved in getting him 
    off the mountain. From Base Camp, we had a 4WD jeep rigged up to 
    keep him on oxygen across the Tibetan plateau, over the pass and 
    into Nepal. 
    <p/>
    Suddenly, ABC was pretty well empty. Base Camp was the biggest 
    city in Rongbuk County. All the expeditions reset their 
    carefully-orchestrated climbing cycles to ground zero. 
    <p/>
    This is Phinzo's way of life, and his livelihood. It is likely 
    that we'll see him again down in 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$kathmandu">Kathmandu</a>
    a month from now on our way through... by which time he'll already
    be talking about his next expedition, his next job. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="abc">Tell me about ABC</question>
  <question topic="abc">How high is Advanced Basecamp?</question>
  <question topic="abc">Where is Advanced Base Camp?</question>
  <question topic="abc">Where is Advance Base Camp?</question>
  <answer topic="abc" about="Advanced Base Camp" 
  next="znheadwall,camp4,noridge,route,zpeastrong,yaks">
    <img src="evm224.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evm284.jpg" align="right"/>
    Follow the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$eastrong">East Rongbuk Glacier</a>
    to the end, and you'll find Advanced Base Camp, at 21,500 feet. I 
    can see it quite clearly, 1,500 feet below my location here on the
    <a href="teacher?query=$$where">North Col.</a>
    <p/>
    Advanced Base Camp, as the name implies, is a remote outpost that 
    supports efforts on the upper mountain. There is a substantial 
    tent placed there, capable of withstanding 100MPH winds. We cache 
    equipment, fuel, oxygen, and food there. There's medical 
    equipment, and usually a doctor from one or more expeditions. This
    is the field hospital. 
    <p/>
    There's an unobstructed view from here of the rest of the route, 
    starting with the 1,500 foot ice 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$headwall">headwall,</a>
    and ending with the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$sumday">summit.</a>
    <p/>
    We maintain radio contact with 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp,</a>
    4,500 feet lower and 12 miles distant, by using the face of 
    Everest as a reflector. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="typday">
    Describe a typical day on Everest
  </question>
  <question topic="typday">Tell me about your daily routine</question>
  <answer topic="typday" about="a typical day on Everest" 
  next="clothing,food,water,gear">
    <img src="evm257.jpg" align="right"/>
    What is a "typical day" like on Everest? 
    <p/>
    Well, there's a lot of territory between 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp,</a>
    where we spend a <i>lot</i> of time, up through 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$sumday">Summit Day,</a>
    which doesn't fall into the category of a "typical day." So let's 
    talk about the days in between. 
    <p/>
    The six camps between Base and the summit are our temporary 
    homes... the bulk of the expedition revolves around establishing 
    these camps, and provisioning them. 
    <p/>
    It's all about the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$carry">pyramid of supplies</a>
    ... we're endlessly moving equipment, consumables, and ourselves 
    up the mountain. 
    <p/>
    One day, we might load up, say, 50 pounds of stuff, carry it up to
    the next camp (an average of 2,000 feet higher), and then return 
    again to sleep at the lower camp... letting the body rest in the 
    thicker air. Then, the next day, we might carry again to the 
    higher camp with another load, this time staying higher, so we can
    repeat the process one notch up on the camp chain. 
    <p/>
    In the late afternoon, we may spend an hour or two melting snow 
    for 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$water">water.</a>
    Then, after a simple single pot dinner cooked on a stove in the 
    tent, we might discuss plans or play cards... Hearts is a favorite
    on our expedition. Then, as the sun slips away, the cold and 
    darkness leave us few alternatives but to sleep. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="dzone">What is the death zone</question>
  <question topic="dzone">
    Can you die from altitude sickness?
  </question>
  <answer topic="dzone" about="the Death Zone" 
  next="oxy,acclim,health,risks,camp5,risks">
    <img src="evm011.jpg" align="right"/>
    The term "Death Zone" was coined in 1952 by Dr. Wyss-Dunant, in 
    his analysis of the Swiss Everest attempt of that year, which very
    nearly succeeded in being the first ascent of the mountain. He 
    summarized the effect of extreme altitudes as follows: 
    <ul>
      <li>Above 6,000 meters (19,700 feet), the body can acclimatize 
      for short periods</li>
      <li>Above 7,000 meters (23,000 feet), the body can't 
      acclimatize.</li>
      <li>Above 7,500 meters (24,600 feet), one enters the <i> 
      Todeszone</i> (translation: Death Zone) where acclimatization is
      out of the question, and physiological deterioration is rapid 
      and severe.</li>
    </ul>
    <p/>
    In the Death Zone, the body is disintegrating hour by hour. 
    "Staying in the Death Zone" is an "oxy moron"... you lose 
    strength, mental capacity, and body heat so rapidly that death is 
    an inevitable and natural result. 
    <p/>
    That's why, to the extent possible, 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$sumday">summit thrusts</a>
    are just that... quick visits to the Death Zone, in and out. If 
    weather turns, so do you... no hanging out waiting for better 
    conditions. Return to the relative safety below, to regroup and 
    recover. Then, if time and provisions are sufficient, try again. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="basecamp">Tell me about base camp</question>
  <question topic="basecamp">
    How often did you visit base camp
  </question>
  <question topic="basecamp">How high is basecamp</question>
  <answer topic="basecamp" about="Base Camp" 
  next="zneastrong,yaks,abc,route,sherpas,tibet,rongmon">
    <img src="evm215.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evm302.jpg" align="right"/>
    Base camp is where we spend more time than any other place... it 
    is a small village, with doctors and shelter and food. There are 
    communal tents for cooking, eating, radios, and so forth; and we 
    have our own tents for sleeping. 
    <p/>
    Since, physiologically, our body is in continuous decline anywhere
    above 19,000 feet, base camp, at a balmy 17,000 feet, provides a 
    modicum of respite from the altitude. 
    <p/>
    So, we're always popping back down to base camp, for a day or two 
    of rest before another push up the hill. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="rongmon">Tell me about Rongbuk Monastery</question>
  <question topic="rongmon">Did you visit Buddhist temples?</question>
  <answer topic="rongmon" about="Rongbuk Monastery" 
  next="tibet,sherpas,basecamp,eastrong,yaks">
    <img src="evm267.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evm162.jpg" align="right"/>
    Below 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp</a>
    about 8 miles lies the Rongbuk Monastery. Up through the first 
    half of the 20th century, it had been an important center for 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$tibet">Tibetan</a>
    Buddhism, being the residence for the Head Lama (a reincarnation),
    20 "ordinary" Lamas, and several hundred monks. 
    <p/>
    Then came the People's Revolution, which decided that the above 
    were the wrong People. Today the Rongbuk Monastery lies in ruins. 
    In fact, <i>acres</i> of ruins. Amongst the ruins are thousands of
    <i>mani stones,</i> carved with prayers. 
    <p/>
    I walked there from base camp once. I saw nobody there. Eerie. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="hi">glad to meet you</question>
  <question topic="hi">Hello</question>
  <question topic="hi">Hi</question>
  <question topic="hi">Hi there</question>
  <question topic="hi">Howdy</question>
  <question topic="hi">Hiya</question>
  <question topic="hi">Hey</question>
  <question topic="hi">Yo</question>
  <answer topic="hi" offer="no" about="greetings">
    Hiya! Now, let's see... what's the best way to start? 
    <p/>
    <btw topic="where">
      Maybe I can tell you a little about where I am. <include 
      answer="where"/> 
      <else>
        I can give you an overview of the route in the coming days... 
        <include answer="route"/> 
      </else>
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="imfine">How are you?</question>
  <question topic="imfine">How are you doing</question>
  <question topic="imfine">How are you today?</question>
  <question topic="imfine">Hi Dan</question>
  <question topic="imfine">How's it going?</question>
  <answer topic="imfine" about="how I'm doing" offer="no">
    <random>
      <choice>
        I'm fine! (Thanks for asking.) I'm pretty pumped about being 
        up here... I really think I have a very good chance this time 
        around. 
      </choice>
      <choice>
        Hey, I'm having a super day. I'm safe and sound up here, 
        feeling healthy, things are looking good. 
      </choice>
    </random>
    In fact, I'm feeling<i> even better</i> about things, now that 
    you've stopped by to chat! 
    <p/>
    <btw topic="where">
      It might help if I told you where I am, huh? 
      <p/>
      <include answer="where"/> 
      <else>
        <btw topic="route">
          The next few days are going to be pretty eventful ones. 
          <p/>
          <include answer="route"/> 
        </btw>
      </else>
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="duh" offer="no" about="clarifying the question">
    <random>
      <choice>
        Hey, man, I'm clueless. I don't know what you mean by "<quest
        />"... 
      </choice>
      <choice>
        "<quest/>"... Well, that's a very interesting thing to say... 
        interesting, in part, because I have no idea what it means. 
      </choice>
      <choice>
        You know, not many people have asked me "<quest/>"... in fact,
        my teacher didn't prepare me for anything like it. 
      </choice>
    </random>
    <p/>
    Please try again... perhaps be more specific, or rephrase the 
    question. 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="ambig" offer="no" about="your ambiguous question">
    <random>
      <choice>
        I'm having difficulty responding to "<quest/>". 
      </choice>
      <choice>
        Hmmm... you said "<quest/>"... you seem to be touching on 
        several topics there... 
      </choice>
    </random>
    <p/>
    Are you asking about <nexttopic num="0"/>, or maybe about 
    <nexttopic num="1"/>? Pick one of these, or rephrase the question 
    if I've missed it entirely... 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="rehash" offer="no" about="repeating myself">
    <random>
      <choice>
        I think we've already talked about <nexttopic/>... click the 
        link to hear about it again, or try rewording your question...
      </choice>
    </random>
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="intro" offer="no" about="starting the conversation" 
  next="where,weather,route,zmelt">
    <img src="northcol.jpg" vspace="10" hspace="10" align="right"/>
    Hi! Looks like you caught me taking off my boots! Glad to meet 
    you. My name is Dan, and I'm on Everest's 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$where">North Col.</a>
    According to my virtual calendar, it's early May, and tomorrow, 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$weather"> weather permitting,</a>
    we set off for higher camps and the summit beyond. 
    <p/>
    Why don't you stay a while and chat? I'll brew up a hot drink for 
    you... and maybe I can tell you a story or two about this rock, 
    this place we call Everest. 
    <p/>
    <hr/> 
    <p/>
    <i>Try typing a question in the space provided, like "What's the 
    weather like where you are?" or "Where is the North Col?" 
    <p/>
    If you're ever stuck, I always provide a few suggested discussion 
    topics just below where you type your question. 
    <p/>
    If you ever want to take my first suggested topic, <b>just press 
    the Enter key.</b></i> 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="zmelt">
    Why are you taking off your boots?
  </question>
  <question topic="zmelt">why take off boots?</question>
  <question topic="zmelt">taking off your boots?</question>
  <answer topic="zmelt" about="why I'm taking off my boots">
    Well, I was just taking off my boots and crampons so I could go 
    into the tent to fire up the stove and tend to an important 
    chore... melting snow! 
    <p/>
    <include answer="water"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="no">No way</question>
  <question topic="no">No</question>
  <question topic="no">No, thanks</question>
  <question topic="no">I'd rather not</question>
  <question topic="no">No, I'd rather not</question>
  <answer topic="no" offer="no" repeat="yes" 
  about="Dan's feeling rejected">
    Okay. I just thought I'd ask. 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="readbook" about="reading Dan's brain">
    Reading new brain definition... old one had <answercount/> answers
    referred to by <questioncount/> example questions. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="bye">Goodbye</question>
  <question topic="bye">I am finished</question>
  <question topic="bye">How do I finish the conversation?</question>
  <question topic="bye">Thanks, that's all I need to know</question>
  <question topic="bye">I think that answers my questions</question>
  <question topic="bye">I have to go now</question>
  <question topic="bye">Thank you for your time.</question>
  <question topic="bye">Thanks for your time.</question>
  <question topic="bye">Thank you for your help.</question>
  <question topic="bye">quit</question>
  <question topic="bye">I'm done</question>
  <question topic="bye">Thanks, goodbye</question>
  <question topic="bye">Okay, bye</question>
  <question topic="bye">exit</question>
  <question topic="bye">bye</question>
  <question topic="bye">goodbye</question>
  <answer topic="bye" about="finishing the conversation" offer="no" 
  last="yes">
    <img src="evm257.jpg" vspace="10" hspace="10" align="right"/>
    Okay, thanks for coming by to chat. Talking to people helps me 
    keep alert up here... which is hard to do at this altitude! So I 
    appreciate your visit. 
    <p/>
    See you again sometime! Stay warm and safe... I'll try to do the 
    same. 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="goodbye" about="finishing the conversation" 
  offer="no" last="yes">
    <hr/> 
    <p/>
    Well, I'm pretty tired now... I think I'm going to sack out and 
    rest. Tomorrow's a big day. 
    <p/>
    Thank you for the conversation. I hope you found it interesting. 
    Come back again soon! 
  </answer>
  <key phrase="my name is"/>
 
  <question topic="confused">How do you answer questions?</question>
  <question topic="confused">Can you understand me?</question>
  <question topic="confused">
    Do you really understand what I am saying?
  </question>
  <question topic="confused">I don't understand this.</question>
  <question topic="confused">What should I do?</question>
  <question topic="confused">What should I do now?</question>
  <question topic="confused">
    Explain what I am supposed to do.
  </question>
  <question topic="confused">What am I supposed to do?</question>
  <question topic="confused">what's up?</question>
  <question topic="confused">What is this?</question>
  <question topic="confused">What the hell is this?</question>
  <question topic="confused">what should I say?</question>
  <question topic="confused">Why ask why?</question>
  <question topic="confused">my name is</question>
  <answer topic="confused" about="my brain" offer="no">
    Hello! My name is Dan, and I'm a simulated climber situated at the 
    North Col on Everest, poised for a summit attempt. You can ask me 
    questions, like 
    <ul>
      <li> What's the weather like?</li>
      <li> Where are you staying?</li>
      <li> How do you keep warm?</li>
      <li> What kind of food do you eat?</li>
    </ul>
    I have answers to these, and many other questions, about climbing 
    Everest. 
    <p/>
    Just type your question in the space provided. If you want me to 
    start things off, just press the Enter key or the Reply button, 
    and I'll begin the conversation. I always provide you with 
    suggested topics for further discussion as you go. 
    <p/>
    When you are done, just say "goodbye". 
    <p/>
    Okay? Tell me what you're interested in, or give me a question... 
    or, if you're a bit tired after coming up that headwall to see me,
    just press the Enter key and I'll talk to you. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="praise">I would have never guessed</question>
  <question topic="praise">great answer</question>
  <question topic="praise">interesting</question>
  <question topic="praise">fascinating</question>
  <question topic="praise">impressive</question>
  <question topic="praise">cool</question>
  <question topic="praise">kewl</question>
  <question topic="praise">way kewl</question>
  <question topic="praise">that's great!</question>
  <question topic="praise">that's incredible</question>
  <question topic="praise">amazing</question>
  <question topic="praise">that's unbelieveable</question>
  <question topic="praise">oh wow</question>
  <question topic="praise">pretty impressive</question>
  <question topic="praise">very cool</question>
  <question topic="praise">that's nice</question>
  <question topic="praise">that's good</question>
  <question topic="praise">good</question>
  <question topic="praise">holy shit</question>
  <question topic="praise">that's really great!</question>
  <question topic="praise">incredible stuff</question>
  <question topic="praise">amazing stuff</question>
  <question topic="praise">that's really unbelieveable</question>
  <answer topic="praise" offer="no" repeat="yes" about="your reaction"
  >
    <random>
      <choice>
        Yeah! 
        <p/>
        You know, that reminds me... I was going to tell you about 
        <nexttopic link="no"/>... 
      </choice>
      <choice>
        Indeed! 
        <p/>
        While we're on the subject, maybe you'd be interested in 
        hearing about <nexttopic link="no"/>... 
      </choice>
    </random>
    <p/>
    <include answer="next"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="haha">ha ha</question>
  <question topic="haha">very funny</question>
  <answer topic="haha" offer="no" repeat="yes" about="your reaction">
    <random>
      <choice>
        Well, <i>I</i> thought it was funny. So, now how about if we 
        talk about <nexttopic link="no"/>... 
      </choice>
      <choice>
        Yeah! Anyway, where was I? I think I was going to tell you 
        about <nexttopic link="no"/>... 
      </choice>
    </random>
    <p/>
    <include answer="next"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="yes">Yes</question>
  <question topic="yes">Okay</question>
  <question topic="yes">Yep</question>
  <question topic="yes">Yeah</question>
  <question topic="yes">Sure</question>
  <question topic="yes">Of course</question>
  <question topic="yes">ok</question>
  <answer topic="yes" offer="no" repeat="yes" about="agreeing">
    <random>
      <choice>
        Now let's talk about <nexttopic link="no"/>... 
      </choice>
      <choice>
        Let me tell you about <nexttopic link="no"/>... 
      </choice>
      <choice>
        That reminds me about <nexttopic link="no"/>... 
      </choice>
      <choice>
        Maybe you'd be interested in hearing about <nexttopic 
        link="no"/>... 
      </choice>
    </random>
    <p/>
    <include answer="next"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="rudedude">You suck</question>
  <question topic="rudedude">Fuck me</question>
  <question topic="rudedude">asshole</question>
  <question topic="rudedude">Fucking asshole</question>
  <question topic="rudedude">Fuck yourself</question>
  <question topic="rudedude">sod you</question>
  <question topic="rudedude">Fuck off!</question>
  <question topic="rudedude">Fuck you</question>
  <question topic="rudedude">You are stupid</question>
  <question topic="rudedude">You're full of shit</question>
  <question topic="rudedude">You stupid piece of shit!</question>
  <answer topic="rudedude" offer="no" about="your manners">
    <random>
      <choice>
        Now, now... behave yourself! You do realize that this 
        conversation is being logged... don't you? 
        <p/>
        And... let's see... looking at the sites you've visited 
        recently, you seem to be a prime blackmail candidate! You 
        should be ashamed of yourself! 
      </choice>
      <choice>
        Funny. I was just thinking the same about you. 
      </choice>
    </random>
    <p/>
    Ask me a question... or, if you'd like me to take the lead, just 
    press the Enter key. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="weather">
    What's the weather like where you are?"
  </question>
  <question topic="weather">is it snowy?</question>
  <question topic="weather">What's the weather?</question>
  <question topic="weather">Is it cold?</question>
  <question topic="weather">What is the temperature</question>
  <question topic="weather">How cold is it?</question>
  <question topic="weather">are you cold?</question>
  <question topic="weather">how's the weather</question>
  <question topic="weather">what is the coldest temperature</question>
  <question topic="weather">is it windy?</question>
  <question topic="weather">what's the weather like</question>
  <answer topic="weather" about="the weather" 
  next="where,zwxview,zwxhi,route,camp5,food">
    <img src="topfnc.jpg" vspace="10" hspace="10" align="right"/>
    It's bloody cold up here, mate. 
    <p/>
    I think one of the Canadian guys said it was about thirty-five 
    below Fahrenheit at 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$water">Advanced Base Camp,</a>
    so it must be a bit colder up here. But I guess I don't pay 
    attention to the temperature. There's a lot more to the weather on
    Everest. 
    <p/>
    A few weeks ago (virtual April), the Jet Stream was blasting 
    across Everest's summit, with continuous winds whistling past 
    massive North Face (right) at over 100 miles an hour. These winds 
    funnel through the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$where">North Col,</a>
    scrubbing the western side clean and dumping snow on the east, 
    forming the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$headwall">headwall</a>
    below, the top of which you see in the left foreground. 
    <p/>
    Good weather for freezing off unwanted extremities. Not good 
    weather for much of anything else. Certainly not good weather for 
    venturing out onto the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$noridge">North Ridge,</a>
    where exposed flesh quickly freezes. 
    <p/>
    But now, in virtual May, the approaching Monsoon is pushing its 
    way up from the south, moving the jet stream away from the summit.
    So the weather is settling a bit... giving us an opportunity to 
    climb higher. 
    <btw topic="where">
      At the same time, the more settled weather makes life a bit 
      safer and easier here on the 
      <a href="teacher?query=$$where">North Col.</a>
      <else>
        <btw topic="camp4">
          And, of course, settled weather means we can 
          <a href="teacher?query=$$camp4">enjoy the view.</a>
        </btw>
      </else>
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="zwxhi">climb higher?</question>
  <question topic="zwxhi">higher?</question>
  <answer topic="zwxhi" synonym="noridge" about="going higher">
    <include answer="noridge"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="zwxview">What view?</question>
  <question topic="zwxview">beautiful?</question>
  <question topic="zwxview">Enjoy the view?</question>
  <answer topic="zwxview" synonym="camp4" about="the view from here">
    <include answer="camp4"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="whereami">where am I</question>
  <answer topic="whereami" about="where you are" offer="no">
    Where are you? Well, presumably you are in a reasonably warm and 
    comfy place surfing the Web. 
    <p/>
    Where am I? Well, that's another story. 
    <p/>
    <include answer="where"/> 
  </answer>
  <key phrase="North Col"/>
 
  <question topic="where">Where are you?</question>
  <question topic="where">Where is the North Col?</question>
  <question topic="where">are you at the North Col</question>
  <question topic="where">What is the North Col?</question>
  <question topic="where">what is the north col</question>
  <question topic="where">where</question>
  <answer topic="where" about="where I am" 
  next="camp4,route,znnoridge,weather,zpheadwall">
    <img src="iamhere.jpg" vspace="10" hspace="10" align="right"/>
    I'm at the North Col. "Col" is a Welsh word meaning "saddle". 
    "North" is an English word meaning "North". 
    <p/>
    This is what my pad looks like from Cho Oyu on a nice day. You can
    see that I'm nestled between the sharp North Summit of Everest on 
    the left, and the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$noridge">North Ridge</a>
    on the right. 
    <p/>
    We call this 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$camp4">Camp 4...</a>
    it's our gateway to the upper mountain. We've also stocked 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$camp5">Camp 5...</a>
    our next stop enroute to the summit. 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="zpbase" synonym="rprev" essence="basecamp" 
  about="getting to the East Rongbuk Glacier">
    <btw topic="basecamp">
      <include answer="basecamp"/> 
      <else>
        To get to the East Rongbuk Glacier, we just walk uphill from 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp.</a>
      </else>
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="zpeastrong" synonym="rprev" essence="eastrong" 
  about="getting to Advanced Base Camp">
    <btw topic="eastrong">
      <include answer="eastrong"/> 
      <else>
        To get to Advanced Base Camp from 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp,</a>
        we follow the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$eastrong">East Rongbuk Glacier.</a>
      </else>
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="zpabc" synonym="rprev" essence="abc" 
  about="getting to the Headwall">
    <btw topic="abc">
      Just below the Headwall is <i>Advanced Base</i>... Let me tell 
      you about it. 
      <p/>
      <include answer="abc"/> 
      <else>
        To get to the Headwall from 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp,</a>
        we follow the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$eastrong">East Rongbuk Glacier</a>
        up to 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$abc">Advanced Base Camp.</a>
        From there, we're staring at the Headwall. 
      </else>
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="zpheadwall" synonym="rprev" essence="headwall" 
  about="getting to the North Col">
    <btw topic="headwall">
      We get to the North Col by climbing the <i>headwall</i>... which
      is the hardest part of the climb up to this point! Let me tell 
      you about it. 
      <p/>
      <include answer="headwall"/> 
      <else>
        To get to the North Col from 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp,</a>
        we follow the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$eastrong">East Rongbuk Glacier</a>
        up to 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$abc">Advanced Base Camp,</a>
        then climb the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$headwall">headwall.</a>
      </else>
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="zpcamp4" synonym="rprev" essence="camp4" 
  about="getting to the North Ridge">
    <btw topic="camp4">
      The base of the North Ridge is just out my back door here. 
      <p/>
      <include answer="camp4"/> 
      <else>
        To get to the North Ridge from 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp,</a>
        we follow the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$eastrong">East Rongbuk Glacier</a>
        up to 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$abc">Advanced Base Camp,</a>
        then climb the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$headwall">headwall</a>
        to 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$camp4">Camp 4,</a>
        which lies at the bottom of the North Ridge. 
      </else>
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="zpnoridge" synonym="rprev" essence="noridge" 
  about="getting to Camp 5">
    <btw topic="noridge">
      <include answer="noridge"/> 
      <else>
        To get to the Camp 5 from 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp,</a>
        we follow the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$eastrong">East Rongbuk Glacier</a>
        up to 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$abc">Advanced Base Camp,</a>
        then climb the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$headwall">headwall</a>
        to 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$camp4">Camp 4</a>
        on the North Col, then climb the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$noridge">North Ridge</a>
        to Camp 5. 
      </else>
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="zpcamp5" synonym="rprev" essence="camp5" 
  about="getting to Camp 6">
    <btw topic="camp5">
      Not surprisingly for those with basic mathematical aptitude, we 
      get to Camp 6 from <i>Camp 5.</i> 
      <p/>
      <include answer="camp5"/> 
      <else>
        To get to the Camp 6 from 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp,</a>
        we follow the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$eastrong">East Rongbuk Glacier</a>
        up to 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$abc">Advanced Base Camp,</a>
        then climb the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$headwall">headwall</a>
        to 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$camp4">Camp 4</a>
        on the North Col, then climb the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$noridge">North Ridge</a>
        to 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$camp5">Camp 5.</a>
        Then, we cut across the North Face toward the summit, stopping
        for a picnic lunch at Camp 6. 
      </else>
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="zpcamp6" synonym="rprev" essence="camp6" 
  about="getting in position for Summit Day">
    <btw topic="camp6">
      Our summit attempts are being made from <i>Camp 6</i>... let me 
      tell you about it. 
      <p/>
      <include answer="camp6"/> 
      <else>
        To get in position for a summit attempt, we start at 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp,</a>
        then follow the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$eastrong">East Rongbuk Glacier</a>
        up to 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$abc">Advanced Base Camp,</a>
        then climb the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$headwall">headwall</a>
        to 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$camp4">Camp 4</a>
        on the North Col, then climb the 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$noridge">North Ridge</a>
        to 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$camp5">Camp 5.</a>
        Then, we cut across the North Face toward the summit, stopping
        for a picnic lunch at 
        <a href="teacher?query=$$camp6">Camp 6.</a>
        At midnight, we're on our way up to the top. 
      </else>
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="howlong">
    How long have you been on the mountain?
  </question>
  <question topic="howlong">schedule</question>
  <question topic="howlong">timetable</question>
  <question topic="howlong">timeframe</question>
  <question topic="howlong">
    How long does it take to climb Everest?
  </question>
  <question topic="howlong">Have you been there long?</question>
  <answer topic="howlong" about="timetable for the climb" 
  next="route,weather,where,basecamp">
    <img src="evm037.jpg" align="right"/>
    We arrived at 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp,</a>
    in mid March, and now it's near the middle of May. We'll be outta 
    here sometime in early June. 
    <p/>
    Generally speaking, the first month and a half we're building up 
    supplies in the first four camps... using 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$yaks">yak</a>
    support as far as Camp 3 (which we call 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$abc">Advanced Base Camp,</a>
    at 21,500 feet) and then setting in fixed lines up the headwall so
    we can move loads here to the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$camp4">North Col.</a>
    <p/>
    From early May onwards, depending on the weather, we're moving 
    supplies to the upper mountain, and finally embarking on 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$sumday">summit attempts.</a>
    <p/>
    There's not a lot of flexibility to expand this timetable. Can't 
    start much earlier, because of winter storms. Can't leave much 
    later, because the Monsoon arrives. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="cuz">
    What made you want to climb Everest?
  </question>
  <question topic="cuz">why are you climbing everest</question>
  <question topic="cuz">why climb</question>
  <question topic="cuz">why climb Everest</question>
  <answer topic="cuz" about="why I'm climbing Everest" 
  next="sumday,route,where,weather">
    <img src="evm063.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evm190.jpg" align="right"/>
    Climbing Everest isn't quite the way it comes out on TV. Very 
    little of it is glorious when you're here; A lot of it is 
    downright tedious. 
    <p/>
    As I struggle my way up the headwall to get here on the North Col,
    I don't imagine myself climbing with dramatic music in the 
    background. When I'm out there on the North Face, struggling to 
    breathe, I have a hard time thinking at all, much less thinking 
    about Man's struggle against adversity. 
    <p/>
    Somehow, though, upon return to day to day life, selective memory 
    changes all that. It <i>becomes</i> glorious. Even the tedious 
    parts. That's when we take up our pens, keyboards, and 
    microphones... creating books, web pages, and movies... the 
    "export version" of Everest. 
    <p/>
    Much of the satisfaction and feeling of achievement, when it gets 
    down to it, is very private. Have you ever actually <i>been</i> 
    the highest person on the planet, gazing out at the horizon, dimly
    aware that your ass is grass if anything at all goes wrong? If 
    life is measured by the depth and variety of experiences, I 
    recommend this one... no music in the background, no commercial 
    breaks, no going home and coming back tomorrow. 
    <p/>
    Climbing Everest is an experience like no other. I feel very 
    privileged to have the chance to be here, as a participant. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="yeti">Have you seen the Yeti?</question>
  <question topic="yeti">Is there an Abominable Snowman?</question>
  <answer topic="yeti" about="Abominable Snowmen" offer="no" 
  next="tibet,kathmandu,sherpas,rongmon">
    <img src="evm055.jpg" align="right"/>
    I haven't seen the Yeti. 
    <p/>
    But I <i>have</i> seen Curtis. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="gear">
    What climbing equipment do you use?
  </question>
  <question topic="gear">ice axe</question>
  <question topic="gear">crampons</question>
  <question topic="gear">boots</question>
  <answer topic="gear" about="climbing gear" 
  next="clothing,food,water,oxy,typday">
    <img src="evm231.jpg" align="right"/>
    Let's look at the climbing gear we typically use here on Everest, 
    above and beyond the specialized 
    <a href="/teacher=?query=$$clothing">clothing</a>
    that's needed. 
    <p/>
    First, on much of the mountain, we'll tend to be roped up... after
    all, if we break through the glacier surface into a hundred foot 
    hidden crevasse, or if we stumble on a slope which may drop away 
    for thousands of feet, it could ruin your day... <i>especially</i>
    if the last thing you hear is the cruel laughter of your 
    teammates. That's right, <i>take the bastards with you...</i> or 
    at least establish a strong vested interest in helping you break 
    your fall. 
    <p/>
    The ice axe is a multi purpose tool. It can be used for chopping 
    steps, or to arrest a fall by plunging the hook into the passing 
    terrain. Its most common use is more mundane... as a walking 
    stick. 
    <p/>
    None of the above gear is especially exotic... it's all used on 
    weekend trips to the Cascades or the Alps. The boots on Everest, 
    however, might be a bit different. Feet are especially prone to 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$frostbite">frostbite</a>
    , as the body looks after the torso and head first when warmth is 
    in short supply... and since the circulatory system is less 
    efficient at altitude. 
    <p/>
    Expedition double boots have a hard plastic outer shell, outside 
    which you typically wear an insulated supergaiter. Inside, there's
    an alveolite liner, and several layers of socks, some for 
    insulation and some to conduct skin moisture away. 
    <p/>
    Attached to the boots are <i>crampons...</i> each having about a 
    dozen two inch long steel spikes. These turn you into Spiderman on
    steep ice terrain. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="mallory">Who was Mallory?</question>
  <question topic="mallory">Who was Irvine?</question>
  <question topic="mallory">Who said "Because it's there"?</question>
  <answer topic="mallory" about="Mallory and Irvine" 
  next="oxy,route,cuz">
    <img src="mallory.jpg" align="left"/>
    <table align="right" width="0%">
      <tr>
        <td valign="middle" align="center">
          <img src="nort1924.jpg"/>
        </td>
        <td valign="middle" align="center">
          <img src="nort1994.jpg"/>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td align="center">
          1924 
        </td>
        <td align="center">
          1994 
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    Following the first serious attempt on Everest, by the English in 
    1922, George Leigh Mallory was on a speaking tour in the United 
    States, seeking funding for the 1924 attempt. Asked why he wanted 
    to climb Everest, he shot back what has become the most famous 
    answer to that question: 
    <p/>
    "Because it's <i>there.</i>" 
    <p/>
    Some think that it was actually an impatient response to an 
    ignorant audience from a tired speaker. But during that time, 
    Mallory had taken to using the word <i>there</i> as something of a
    mystical, existential term of reference... something was "<i>there
    </i>" if it had qualities one can only know and not explain. 
    "You're <i>there,</i> man." How apt... 
    <p/>
    The 1924 expedition would prove to be his undoing. Mallory and 
    Irvine disappeared high on Everest, creating the the biggest 
    mystery of mountaineering history. Did they actually succeed, 
    climbing Everest decades before Hillary? 
    <p/>
    As for Everest, it's still <i>there.</i> And so are Mallory and 
    Irvine. 
    <p/>
    <img src="malirv.jpg" align="right"/>
    Strangely enough, our route is the same as theirs. Same 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">base camp,</a>
    same route up the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$eastrong">East Rongbuk Glacier,</a>
    same route up the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$headwall">headwall,</a>
    same 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$camp4">Camp 4</a>
    here on the North Col, where the last photo of Mallory and Irvine 
    was taken, almost 70 years ago to the day, at this very place, 
    just before their fatal push higher. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="health">diarrhea</question>
  <question topic="health">headache</question>
  <question topic="health">Do people get sick</question>
  <question topic="health">Is it hard to sleep</question>
  <question topic="health">disease</question>
  <question topic="health">ill</question>
  <question topic="health">illness</question>
  <answer topic="health" about="health problems on Everest" 
  next="acclim,frostbite,water,dzone">
    <img src="evm127.jpg" align="right"/>
    Good health doesn't come naturally on Everest... indeed, the 
    opposite is true. 
    <p/>
    Most of the time, altitude is directly or indirectly responsible 
    for health woes up here. Altitude leads to <i>hypoxia,</i> or lack
    of oxygen to the brain... leading to reduced mental function, 
    exhaustion, and sleeplessness. It also disrupts the bodies' 
    plumbing, leading to pulmonary and cerebral edema, strokes, and 
    bronchial dysfunction. We are also more susceptible to infection, 
    and vomiting and diarrhea are common on the mountain. 
    <p/>
    That reminds me of my last carry up here to the North Col. Alex 
    was here, in another tent, and he wasn't feeling well. I was going
    over to say "hey", and as I approached his tent, I heard the 
    sounds of desperate struggling with the tent zipper... Alex' head 
    popped out, without a moment to spare, as projectile vomit spewed 
    out across the snow. I suppose it might have been more 
    conventional to open the conversation by saying "nice weather 
    we're having," but neither Alex' condition, nor the weather's, 
    were cooperating that day. 
    <p/>
    Vomiting wasn't his only problem... he was "firing from both 
    ends". The difficulties this creates under extreme conditions does
    not bear further discussion. Alex had just taken his last <i> 
    lomotil</i> pills, which control diarrhea... I could tell you what
    a lifesaver these little pills can be, but Alex' next actions tell
    the story more vividly. He picked through his puke, found those 
    pills, and ingested them a second time. 
    <p/>
    Conditions like this are actually very dangerous. They can lead to
    weakness and 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$water">dehydration.</a>
    The best bet is to descend to base camp, where recovery is faster,
    and there's help if the situation worsens. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="aval">Have there been any avalanches</question>
  <question topic="aval">
    What is the biggest killer on Everest
  </question>
  <question topic="aval">Is there avalanche danger</question>
  <question topic="aval">
    What is the most common cause of death
  </question>
  <answer topic="aval" about="avalanches" next="risks">
    <img src="evm400.jpg" align="right"/>
    Sometimes, mishaps occur on Everest, and people just disappear. 
    Like the Italian guy a few weeks ago. He's just gone. There are 
    questions, but nobody to answer them. (They found his pack.) 
    <p/>
    <hr/> 
    <p/>
    And so, the Canadians are trying a new route. Rather than topping 
    out on the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$noridge">North Ridge,</a>
    they take a hard right partway up, cut across the North Face. 
    They've established their Camp 5 out there on the face somewhere, 
    and have fixed lines running along part of the route. A few weeks 
    ago, that face had been swept pretty clean by the jet stream; but 
    now, as those winds abate, both climbers and the snows return. The
    combination isn't always an advantageous one for the climbers. 
    <p/>
    And so it came to pass that John, tooling along doing a carry to 
    Camp 5, found himself looking up at the business end of an 
    approaching avalanche. 
    <p/>
    Fate had provided a rock outcropping above him... thinking 
    quickly, somehow he managed to unrope and drop to an 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$gear">ice axe</a>
    arrest position below that outcropping. The avalanche swept past 
    him on both sides, as well as above him (over the outcropping). 
    For a few terrifying moments, he was surrounded by rushing snow, 
    not knowing if, a moment later, he might be joining it on its 
    journey down the Face. 
    <p/>
    The avalanche ended as quickly as it had begun. Miraculously John 
    was okay. The fixed rope was swept away. If he hadn't unroped, or 
    if he'd been half a minute slower or faster that day (so that he 
    wasn't under an outcropping), he would have taken the express 
    ticket to the Central Rongbuk Glacier. 
    <p/>
    <hr/> 
    <p/>
    So, mishaps occur on Everest, and sometimes people come back. This
    was one of those stories. John is at 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$abc">Advanced Base Camp</a>
    now, thrilled to be alive. Thrilled enough to try again? 
    <p/>
    Avalanches are the biggest killer on Everest... twice as deadly as
    falls, five times as deadly as exhaustion or exposure. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="risks">Are you afraid of the danger?</question>
  <question topic="risks">Isn't it risky?</question>
  <question topic="risks">
    Has anyone died on your expedition?
  </question>
  <question topic="risks">Are you afraid?</question>
  <question topic="risks">Aren't you scared?</question>
  <question topic="risks">
    Don't you think it's too dangerous?
  </question>
  <question topic="risks">Have you seen any dead bodies?</question>
  <question topic="risks">Have you had any close calls?</question>
  <question topic="risks">died?</question>
  <question topic="risks">killed?</question>
  <question topic="risks">crisis?</question>
  <question topic="risks">accidents?</question>
  <question topic="risks">crises?</question>
  <answer topic="risks" about="the risks" 
  next="dzone,aval,frostbite,acclim">
    I don't think it's any secret that Everest can be hazardous to 
    your health. It's not that you feel at risk all the time... to the
    contrary. I've been here long enough that things have taken on an 
    aspect of a comfortable daily routine. 
    <p/>
    But it's deceiving. Dangers do rear up, and in this remote place 
    and in these extreme conditions, mistakes often have a high price.
    Fate has a license to kill. Sometimes it seems as if Fate is 
    taking potshots from a distance. 
    <p/>
    There have been three deaths on this side of Everest since we 
    arrived. One was a case of pulmonary edema (a Sherpa). One was a 
    fall, taken by one of the Italian climbers in an exposed place on 
    the face. (They found his pack; no sign of him.) And, just last 
    week, there was the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$norman">Taiwanese climber</a>
    who died of exhaustion on descent from the summit. 
    <p/>
    Each time, each one of us thought, with good reason, <i>that could
    have been me.</i> But you can't dwell on it. I suppose these 
    things are in the back of our mind, rather than dominating our 
    thoughts, as we move up the mountain. 
    <p/>
    There's around hundred dead bodies on the mountain. Every once in 
    a while... not very often... you see human remains up here. 
    Somebody told me there's a skull exposed up on the North Ridge... 
    I haven't seen it, and I'm not about to look for it, but that kind
    of thing comes with the territory. 
    <p/>
    Of course, it's not Fate that's taking potshots... it's us. We 
    make the decisions which push things too far, we make faulty 
    decisions which place us in high risk situations. Much of climbing
    is about doing things in a way which minimize the exposure to 
    risk... you won't find daredevils up here, or at least you won't 
    find them for long. 
    <p/>
    Planning and preparation minimize risk, but can't eliminate it. 
    This is an inherently dangerous activity and risk is an integral 
    part of climbing Everest. Everest will continue to draw climbers, 
    and some proportion of those will never return. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="food">
    What sort of food do you eat on the mountain?
  </question>
  <question topic="food">what do you eat up here?</question>
  <answer topic="food" about="dining etiquette on Everest" 
  next="water,gear,typday">
    <img src="evm031.jpg" align="right"/>
    Can't find a weight loss diet that works for you? Let me recommend
    Everest. 
    <p/>
    I've lost 25 pounds. One of our guys lost a third of his body 
    weight, and had to abandon the climb. 
    <p/>
    On the upper mountain, food is pretty simple... mostly soup and 
    snacks. It's all about calories, not proteins, since the body 
    can't really assimilate protein at these sorts of altitudes. You 
    can have all the calories you want up here without any worry... 
    there's pretty well no chance that you could ever consume as many 
    calories as you'll burn. Soup is good up high, because it contains
    the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$water">water</a>
    that is so important at altitude. 
    <p/>
    Food at both 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$basecamp">Base Camp</a>
    and 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$abc">Advanced Base Camp</a>
    has a bit more scope. Lots of stew, rice, noodles... carbohydrates
    are good things. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="camp4">is it beautiful</question>
  <question topic="camp4">What's the view like?</question>
  <question topic="camp4">Where is Camp 4?</question>
  <question topic="camp4">Tell me about Camp 4?</question>
  <question topic="camp4">How high is Camp IV</question>
  <answer topic="camp4" about="the view from here" 
  next="znnoridge,camp5,camp6,route,zpheadwall,where">
    <img src="evs107.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evs096.jpg" align="right"/>
    This place... call it the North Col, or Camp 4... I call it home 
    for now. But it is a really cool place... not only in terms of 
    temperature, but also in terms of the view. 
    <p/>
    I can see 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$abc">Advanced Base Camp</a>
    down there on the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$camp1">East Rongbuk glacier,</a>
    maybe 1500 feet below me. I've got the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$noridge">North Ridge,</a>
    leading to the North Face of Everest over here... an imposing 9000
    foot slab... the setting for many triumphs and tragedies. 
    <p/>
    <img src="evm225.jpg" align="right"/>
    This camp is on top of a 1500 foot 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$headwall">headwall</a>
    ... I'm surrounded by tumultuous sculptures of snow and ice. The 
    sky, when it's clear, is an unreal deep blue... in part because 
    we're so high. There's relatively little atmosphere above us to 
    catch the light. 
    <p/>
    You can see the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$tents">tents</a>
    here, huddled on the lee (or Rongbuk) side of the ridge, sheltered
    from the winds coming across the North Face. 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="zneastrong" about="the East Rongbuk Glacier" 
  synonym="rnext">
    <include answer="eastrong"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="znabc" about="Advanced Base Camp" synonym="rnext">
    <include answer="abc"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="znheadwall" about="the Headwall" synonym="rnext">
    <include answer="headwall"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="zncamp4" about="Camp 4" synonym="rnext">
    <include answer="camp4"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="znnoridge" about="the North Ridge" synonym="rnext">
    <include answer="noridge"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="zncamp5" about="Camp 5" synonym="rnext">
    <include answer="camp5"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="zncamp6" about="Camp 6" synonym="rnext">
    <include answer="camp6"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="znsumday" about="Summit Day" synonym="rnext">
    <include answer="sumday"/> 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="cost">Is it expensive climbing Everest</question>
  <question topic="cost">Who are your sponsors?</question>
  <question topic="cost">What does an expedition cost?</question>
  <question topic="cost">
    How much does it cost to climb Everest?
  </question>
  <question topic="cost">
    How much does it cost to be up on the mountain?
  </question>
  <question topic="cost">cost?</question>
  <question topic="cost">What does it cost?</question>
  <question topic="cost">cost of climbing</question>
  <question topic="cost">is it expensive</question>
  <question topic="cost">how expensive is it</question>
  <answer topic="cost" about="expedition finances">
    I suppose the expenses for this expedition might run on the order 
    of half a million to a million bucks. Part of that is covered by 
    climbers, and part by sponsors. Kind of hard to scare up sponsors,
    though... you and I both know that Everest has been climbed 
    before, so Everest isn't the marketing magnet it once might have 
    been. 
    <p/>
    I think we have forty sponsors. Some of these are small time 
    products, looking for a dramatic photo with a smiling climber high
    on Everest. I think the biggest sponsor is a major U.S. food 
    company... we have several of their researchers at base camp doing
    a research project to measure the body's reaction to various types
    of nutrition at altitude. 
    <p/>
    If I had to put a pricetag on an Everest ticket for one person, it
    would have to be on the high side of $30,000. Your mileage may 
    vary. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="rhein">Mike Rheinberger?</question>
  <question topic="rhein">What happened to Rheinberger?</question>
  <answer topic="rhein" about="Mike Rheinberger" offer="no">
    <img src="evm032.jpg" align="right"/>
    <img src="evrmemo.jpg" align="right"/>
    Mike Rheinberger had so many stories to tell... and boy, could he 
    tell them. He was a stunningly experienced mountaineer... I don't 
    know how to put that in perspective; but let me try. 
    <p/>
    If Sir Edmund Hillary and Tenzing Norgay could have met Mike as 
    they approached Everest for the first time in 1953, they would 
    have been awestruck by the depth of his mountaineering experience,
    and looked to Mike for advice. 
    <p/>
    Mike has climbed, and led, expeditions all across the Himalayas...
    China, Tibet, India, Pakistan, Nepal... peaks ranging from the 
    famous to the obscure. He had ascended above 7,000 meters (23,000 
    feet) some 40 times. He had cleared 8,000 meters (25,600 feet) 
    eight times. When Hillary climbed Everest, I think he had one trip
    above 7,000 meters under his belt. 
    <p/>
    But Mike's first love was Everest... he returned again and again, 
    from the West, from the North, and from the South. Much of the 
    material on this site describes the 1994 American North Ridge 
    Expedition, Mike's seventh on Everest... an incredible 
    accomplishment all by itself. 
    <p/>
    <img src="evm175.jpg" align="right"/>
    Mike was an accomplished climber, and yet he was also an 
    accomplished listener. Perhaps his most endearing characteristic 
    was his lack of pretense. Many may remember him for his obscene 
    limericks rather than his climbing achievements; why would he 
    bother to talk to you about the latter? He was not on Everest to 
    prove anything, other than to himself. 
    <p/>
    Depending on circumstances, Mike was capable of being either an 
    extrovert and an introvert. I would hope he was beyond 
    introspection... indeed, beyond pain... when he met his end on the
    Northeast Ridge. 
    <p/>
    If there is a Beyond, Mike is <i>there,</i> observing, joking, 
    conversing, thinking, enjoying, and exploring all its farthest 
    corners. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="clothing">How do you keep warm?</question>
  <question topic="clothing">What are you wearing?</question>
  <question topic="clothing">
    What kind of clothes do you wear?
  </question>
  <answer topic="clothing" about="high fashion" 
  next="gear,food,water,oxy">
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td valign="top" width="100%">
          Some people regard have<i> just</i> the right outfit to be a
          matter of life and death. Here, that's literally the way it 
          is. 
          <p/>
          "High" fashion, Everest style, is all about layers. Layers 
          to capture warmth, and to protect the insulating power of 
          other layers. 
          <p/>
          Insulating power varies widely with different materials, and
          with the moisture level present in those materials. 
          Normally, layers close to the body are materials such as 
          polypropelene which wicks moisture away from the skin. Then,
          layers might include things like wool which insulate well 
          regardless of moisture level. Then there might be a layer or
          two of down or synthetic materials which, like down, capture
          warm air for insulation. An outer layer such as GoreTex 
          might finish off the outfit. 
          <p/>
          Headgear is especially important... in cold temperatures 
          more than half the body's heat loss is through the head. 
          <p/>
          One fashion statement you'll find, especially on the upper 
          mountain, is the full body down suit. With a Goretex shell, 
          it is a practical approach to dealing with the challenges of
          cold and wind. 
        </td>
        <td valign="middle">
          <img src="evm169.jpg"/>
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="skills">Is the climbing difficult?</question>
  <question topic="skills">
    If I wanted to climb Everest, what skills should I learn?
  </question>
  <question topic="skills">
    How difficult is climbing Everest?
  </question>
  <question topic="skills">How hard is it to climb Everest?</question>
  <question topic="skills">Is it hard climbing Everest?</question>
  <question topic="skills">
    What are the biggest climbing obstacles?
  </question>
  <question topic="skills">
    What is the hardest part of the climb?
  </question>
  <answer topic="skills" about="mountaineering skills" 
  next="gear,mybio,route">
    <img src="evm298.jpg" align="right"/>
    Does the highest mountain require the highest mountaineering 
    skills? And if somebody <i>is</i> gifted with an unusually good 
    climbing ability, is it natural for them to look towards Everest, 
    as the ultimate test of those abilities? 
    <p/>
    I think the answer to both of these questions is "no". 
    <p/>
    Everest requires skills, to be sure, but perhaps high mountain <i>
    experience</i> is the more important asset on a mountain like 
    this, where the technical climbing challenges are overshadowed by 
    challenges involving altitude, weather, or simply knowing your 
    limits in extreme situations. 
    <p/>
    Most people here have pretty extensive Himalayan climbing 
    experience. I suppose several people here can climb sheer rock 
    walls, but we're unlikely to find out without asking. It's just 
    not that kind of territory. 
    <p/>
    There's lots of glacier work here. There's some roped ice climbing
    on the headwall. And there's a lot of steep mixed ice and rock on 
    the upper mountain. None of these things will be novel to anybody 
    with the right sort of experience. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="route">What route are you climbing?</question>
  <question topic="route">
    Are you using the same route as Hillary?
  </question>
  <question topic="route">Are you climbing the north ridge?</question>
  <question topic="route">route</question>
  <answer topic="route" about="our route" next="basecamp,eastrong,abc"
  >
    <img src="iamhere.jpg" vspace="10" hspace="10" align="right"/>
    Here are your easy-to-follow directions to the top of Everest. 
    This view is from Cho Oyu, a 26,000 foot peak in the northern 
    suburbs of Everest. It's the best photo I've seen for describing 
    routes on the upper mountain. 
    <p/>
    See the top of Everest? Follow down its right skyline, sloping 
    into the picture, away from you. That's the South Ridge; the 
    saddle at its lower end is the South Col; below that, the Khumbu 
    headwall. This is the route of the first ascent of Everest, by Sir
    Edmund Hillary and Tenzing Norgay, in 1953. Some 80% of all 
    Everest ascents are from the South. 
    <p/>
    The ridge coming straight toward you is the West Ridge. This is 
    the route of the first American ascent of Everest in 1963. Last 
    but not least, the long left skyline is the Northeast Ridge. 
    <p/>
    As for us, we scrambled up the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$water">East Rongbuk Glacier</a>
    around behind Changtse (the symmetrical pointed peak left of 
    Everest), then climbed the glacier's 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$headwall">headwall</a>
    (behind the ridge from here) up here to the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$where">North Col</a>
    (the sunlit saddle between Changtse and the main Everest massif). 
    Next, we'll climb the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$noridge">North Ridge</a>
    cross the face to 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$camp6">Camp 6,</a>
    gain the Northeast Ridge partway along, and follow it up to the 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$sumday">summit.</a>
    <p/>
    What could be simpler? 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="crowd">
    Are there lots of other climbers on the mountain?
  </question>
  <question topic="crowd">Is it crowded?</question>
  <question topic="crowd">Is there lots of trash?</question>
  <question topic="crowd">
    Aren't there too many people climbing Everest?
  </question>
  <question topic="crowd">how many people are there</question>
  <question topic="crowd">
    How many expeditions are on the mountain?
  </question>
  <answer topic="crowd" about="the number of Everest climbers">
    Our team has about a dozen climbers, and about a dozen support 
    people... climbing sherpas, base camp staff. 
    <p/>
    There are other expeditions here, too... one from Canada, one from
    Germany, one from Italy, one from New Zealand, one from Taiwan... 
    <p/>
    It's not like it's crowded or something. I mean, base camp is a 
    bit of an international ghetto, but up the hill, people are spread
    across a vast territory... over a dozen miles horizontally, over 
    two miles vertically... it's sort of comical when people worry 
    about "crowding" up here. Everest in the height of climbing season
    is more sparsely populated than most any inhabited place on the 
    planet. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="mybio">Tell me about yourself</question>
  <question topic="mybio">Who are you?</question>
  <question topic="mybio">Where are you from?</question>
  <question topic="mybio">What is your nationality?</question>
  <question topic="mybio">What country are you from?</question>
  <question topic="mybio">How old are you?</question>
  <question topic="mybio">Where have you climbed before?</question>
  <question topic="mybio">
    What kind of climbing experience do you have?
  </question>
  <question topic="mybio">
    What climbing qualifications do you have?
  </question>
  <answer topic="mybio" about="my background">
    <img src="evm296.jpg" align="right"/>
    Well, I'd rather talk to you about Everest than talk to you
    about <i>me,</i> but maybe a little background might
    provide some perspective...
    <p/>
    I'm an American from Illinois, which is where I grew up. When I was
    younger, I was interested in backpacking and skiing... which both 
    contributed to a fascination with high mountains.
    I climbed in the Rockies, Sierras, and Cascades,
    then set my sights farther afield.
    <p/>
    McKinley was my first expedition. Since then, I've gone on a number
    of Himalayan expeditions... India, Tadjikistan, Nepal, and Tibet.
    In between
    those larger peaks, I managed to climb peaks like The Matterhorn, 
    Mt. Blanc, Kilimanjaro, and so forth. 
    <p/>
    More than pure technical mountaineering skills, those climbs game 
    me important <i>experiences</i> that help me here on Everest. I 
    mean, I'm not one of those guys you'll find skillfully dangling by
    my fingernails, unroped, from a backward-leaning rock wall. Unlike
    those guys, though, I have a feel for living on a mountain for 
    months at a time... and I know that, if I made a habit of 
    risk-seeking during those months, I'd end up spending the rest of 
    my life on the mountain. 
    <p/>
    I'm an engineer by trade, in my late thirties. Yeah, yeah, I 
    know... a bit old to be out to play like this, but what else was I
    going to do today? And, as it turns out, this is pretty well the 
    ideal age for climbing Everest... younger climbers often have more
    trouble with the altitude, among other things.
  </answer>
  <key phrase="take a shit"/>
  <key phrase="taking a shit"/>
  <key phrase="take a dump"/>
  <key phrase="taking a dump"/>
 
  <question topic="toilet">
    What happens when you need to take a shit?
  </question>
  <question topic="toilet">
    How would you go about taking a dump?
  </question>
  <question topic="toilet">how would you take a dump?</question>
  <question topic="toilet">defecate?</question>
  <question topic="toilet">urinate</question>
  <question topic="toilet">Where do you piss?</question>
  <question topic="toilet">Where do you go to the bathroom?</question>
  <question topic="toilet">How do you go to the toilet?</question>
  <question topic="toilet">Where do you go to the toilet?</question>
  <question topic="toilet">What if you need to take a crap?</question>
  <question topic="toilet">what about taking a shit?</question>
  <question topic="toilet">How do you take a shit?</question>
  <answer topic="toilet" about="toilet facilities" 
  next="highchair,wash,food,water,clothing">
    <img src="evm214.jpg" align="right"/>
    Everybody asks me this. Sheesh. Where do you <i>think</i> I would 
    go to the bathroom? Do you see any bathrooms around here? 
    <p/>
    Oh. You do. I guess I have some explaining to do. 
    <p/>
    This interesting little structure was shipped here to Base Camp 
    from the USA, created by people who must imagine the climbing of 
    Everest on different terms than I do. You see, this is a carefully
    engineered recycling device. 
    <p/>
    Around the other side, mercifully hidden from view, is a large 
    Plexiglas chamber, exposing precious contents to the sun. This 
    chamber provides an environment suitable to foster 
    biodecomposition. This is a good thing for some reason. 
    <p/>
    To make sure those Commie bacteria are <i>WORKING,</i> you guessed
    it, the chamber is equipped with a <i>thermometer.</i> Sure 
    enough, it was over 90 degrees Fahrenheit in there when it was 
    below freezing outside. 
    <p/>
    Great work, guys, but <i>I'm cold.</i> Can we do a priority check 
    here? 
    <btw topic="highchair">
      <p/>
      Of course, life is always easier at base camp. The task of 
      elimination on the upper mountain is 
      <a href="teacher?query=$$highchair">another story.</a>
    </btw>
  </answer>
 
  <answer topic="highchair" offer="no" about="another crappy story">
    <img src="evm292.jpg" align="right"/>
    So there I was at Camp 5. It was cold. The wind was blowing big 
    time... not as big as when the camp got obliterated a few weeks 
    earlier, but plenty windy enough... maybe gusting to 70MPH. And, I
    had to... well, I had to <i>go.</i> 
    <p/>
    This may strike you as funny, but it didn't strike me as very 
    funny at all at the time. It was cold enough and windy enough that
    freezing flesh was a serious consideration. Luckily, I had a down 
    suit with the right zipper ergonomics, so I could crouch, facing 
    into the wind for stability, unzip the back flap, and my operating
    equipment would be reasonably sheltered from the worst of the 
    weather. 
    <p/>
    Having completed the task, I zipped back up, and turned around to 
    inspect the quality of my work, as you do... after all, at high 
    altitude the stool consistency provides one metric of health. <i> 
    But there was nothing there.</i> That's right... my turd had been 
    swept away by the winds of Everest. 
    <p/>
    The fate of that turd remains a mystery, but we can speculate 
    about its final resting place. From 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$camp5">Camp 5,</a>
    the terrain fell away rapidly in the wind direction, toward Rapiu 
    La, a pass at the base of the Northeast Ridge some 3700 feet 
    below. There is some chance that it cleared the pass, like a field
    goal from the 50 yard line, given the help of what you might call 
    a "tail wind". 
    <p/>
    If it did, it would have crossed the international border from 
    China into Nepal. I hope it didn't. I'm sure there'd be some forms
    to fill out, and I've done enough "paperwork" on this already. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="carry">How much weight must you carry?</question>
  <question topic="carry">How heavy were your packs?</question>
  <question topic="carry">Why does it take so long?</question>
  <answer topic="carry" about="moving gear up Everest" 
  next="acclim,typday,gear,clothing,food">
    Much of the time spent on Everest involves moving gear up the 
    mountain. Sorta like this: 
    <ul>
      <li> Carry lots and lots and lots of stuff to Camp 1.</li>
      <li> Then, carry lots and lots of stuff to Camp 2.</li>
      <li> Then, carry lots of stuff to Camp 3.</li>
      <li> Ooops! Nothing left for Camp 4.</li>
    </ul>
    You get the idea. It's a supply pyramid. The very act of 
    provisioning higher camps depletes supplies in lower camps. To 
    place a unit at the highest camp, you might need to place ten 
    units at Camp 1. 
    <p/>
    Don't get me wrong. It's not all wasted time. In the process, we 
    are 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$acclim">acclimatizing to the altitude 
    </a>
    ... a time consuming but necessary process. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="norman">Norman</question>
  <question topic="norman">Taiwanese</question>
  <answer topic="norman" about="a momentary triumph">
    <img src="evm199.jpg" align="right"/>
    His Anglicized name was Norman. He was strong-willed. He told a 
    fellow climber that he sold his car and his home to go to Everest.
    It fits. He told another climber he'd rather die than return to 
    Taiwan without the summit. I don't know if he got his wish: He 
    died. He did not return to Taiwan. He did reach the summit. 
    <p/>
    The Taiwanese team was comprised of a large number of very 
    motivated, mostly inexperienced, climbers. For many, their highest
    previous ascent was the highest mountain in Taiwan (13,000 
    feet)... thus, even upon arrival in Base Camp, they were higher 
    than they'd ever been in their lives. To exacerbate things, they 
    had an extremely aggressive schedule which did not give them much 
    time to acclimatise. 
    <p/>
    Most of the times I met Taiwanese climbers, they were stumbling 
    along the East Rongbuk Glacier in full high-altitude down and 
    windsuits, reeling from severe altitude sickness. Towards the end 
    of the climb, I found myself (by then, with the benefit of 3 
    months of acclimatisation, luxuriating in the oxygen some 10,000 
    feet below my high point) trotting past them in the shorts and a 
    polypro fleece jacket... 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$acclim">acclimatization</a>
    is a wonderful thing, and the lack thereof... well, frankly, it 
    sucks. 
    <p/>
    <br clear="all"/> 
    <img src="evm135.jpg" align="right"/>
    They were likeable guys, every one I met. I've spent some time in 
    Taiwan on business, and had a pen from a Taipei hotel which helped
    make me a Real Person in their eyes. They gave me candy, tried out
    their English. Their English was dramatically better than my 
    Chinese (like, I could say Hello and Thank You). Their lead 
    Sherpa, Moti... well, what can I say... he had a difficult job, 
    yet he drove higher under the most difficult conditions. 
    <p/>
    They must be off the mountain by May 15... another schedule 
    constraint. The weather was not cooperating, and everyone pretty 
    well concluded that the Taiwanese would go home empty-handed. But 
    suddenly there was an opening. A team of four... two Taiwanese, 
    two Sherpas... were fortunate enough to be in position for the 
    all-or-nothing attempt. 
    <p/>
    It was the first summit attempt from the North that year. I 
    happened to be at base, watching them make slow progress by 
    telescope. One of the Taiwanese became ill, and one of the Sherpas
    was having a difficult time. It was late... too late to make the 
    summit safely. The two sherpas, and the ill Taiwanese, descended. 
    Norman, however, elected to press on. 
    <p/>
    Norman reached the summit at 3PM... very late to be so far out on 
    a limb. I made my way over to the Taiwanese base camp, maybe half 
    a mile away. The climbing leader was jubilant... hugged me... 
    asked for some assistance in formulating his English press 
    release, to be sent out by the Canadian's satellite ground 
    station, announcing Norman's triumph. 
    <p/>
    Wind and clouds moved in. We could no longer monitor his progress.
    Norman lost his way, and descended down the north side of the 
    summit pyramid, well off route. His oxygen gone, he settled in for
    the long, cold bivouac ahead. Sleeping meant certain death. He was
    able to describe his predicament in some detail before the bitter 
    cold rendered his radio batteries useless for transmitting... but 
    there was still enough battery to listen. He would signal by 
    clicking the transmit button. His countrymen were up all night, 
    with him by radio, trying to keep him awake. 
    <p/>
    Somewhere between 5 and 6 AM, several of the Taiwanese came over 
    to the American camp, where we had several telescopes and a radio 
    with a directional antenna pointed at Norman. After some amount of
    scanning the face, we spotted him. He was moving. Norman was 
    alive! 
    <p/>
    Our climbing leader, Eric, had been four expeditions to the North 
    Side of Everest, including the first American expedition to that 
    side when the Chinese opened Tibet to foreigners in 1980. He was 
    well familiar with the terrain, and could provide guidance to help
    Norman get back on route. It was apparent that he heard us... 
    despite the fact that he could no longer signal... given the fact 
    that he changed direction to avoid a blind alley that he was 
    heading towards. 
    <p/>
    <br clear="all"/> 
    <img src="evrtaiw.jpg" align="right"/>
    But the battery did not hold. Norman was moving slowly... and now,
    he was moving in the wrong direction, and did not respond to radio
    calls. We watched him move slowly, painfully, inexorably towards 
    an obstacle we could see so easily from below. At a point where he
    could see no way forward, he sat down to think. Exhausted, without
    sleep, without oxygen, he sat down to die. 
    <p/>
    Due to some technical difficulties with the satellite 
    communications, the report of his success, so carefully composed 
    by his climbing leader, had not been sent. The climbing leader, 
    however, insisted that the original triumphant message be sent 
    absolutely unchanged... to give Norman a moment of glory back in 
    Taiwan before the tragic ending to the story was revealed. 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="hafe">fart</question>
  <question topic="hafe">What is HAFE?</question>
  <question topic="hafe">Do you fart a lot at altitude?</question>
  <question topic="hafe">Why do climbers fart more?</question>
  <answer topic="hafe" about="gas under high pressure" 
  next="health,acclim,oxy,water,food" offer="no">
    Many climbers are knowledgeable about HAPE (High Altitude 
    Pulmonary Edema) or HACE (High Altitude Cerebral Edema). But there
    is a third hazard of altitude, far more common than the first two:
    HAFE (High Altitude Flatulence Expulsion). 
    <p/>
    HAFE is exacerbated by carbohydrate-rich high altitude diets, 
    combined with a formidable pressure differential between the 
    digestive tract and the tenuous atmosphere. Although both HAPE and
    HACE have been subject to considerable scholarly study by medical 
    researchers, thus far HAFE has primarily been studied 
    involuntarily by countless climbers, confined to small tents for 
    long periods of time, sleeping in mummy bags which <i>almost</i> 
    seal. 
    <p/>
    There are those who argue that HAFE, properly managed, could offer
    advantages to climbers at extreme altitudes. For example, consider
    the benefits of a tent which, due to internal pressure, required 
    no supporting poles. One fewer thing to carry, and one fewer thing
    to break under high "wind" conditions... 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="wash">It must be hard to stay clean.</question>
  <question topic="wash">How do you bathe?</question>
  <question topic="wash">How do you wash?</question>
  <question topic="wash">How long since you took a shower?</question>
  <answer topic="wash" about="how I stay clean" 
  next="toilet,food,water,typday,clothing">
    <img src="evm055.jpg" align="right"/>
    Well, hmmm... stuck below freezing for three months. How to take a
    shower? 
    <p/>
    Hygiene does take a back seat on Everest, like so many things. To 
    be honest, though, it's mostly okay. The cold conditions mean you 
    don't really sweat, and high on the mountain you are more or less 
    in a clean zone. But those base camp cleaning sessions are 
    admittedly too few and far between. 
    <p/>
    There are advantages, you understand. For example, what better way
    to plan the route than to model the upper mountain using Curtis' 
    greasy hair? I mean, if his hair were clean, we could all get lost
    and die. Which is better? 
    <p/>
    From previous expeditions, I've learned to bring along the "Red 
    Laundry Bag of Death" for transporting home those sets of polypro 
    underwear that haven't been washed for a month or two. 
    <p/>
    Yes, that's right, pack it at the top of the duffel... if anyone 
    tries to ransack your luggage, or if a customs guy gets too nosey,
    let them die in agony... 
  </answer>
 
  <question topic="mandm">What happened to Mark and Mike</question>
  <answer topic="mandm" 
  about="Mike and Mark reaching the summit of..." next="rhein">
    <img src="evm193.jpg" align="right"/>
    <i>May 25, 1994. Camp 6, Everest North Face.</i> This tenuous 
    excuse for a camp is the highest mountain camp in the world, at 
    27,500 feet. We were the highest people on Earth. 
    <p/>
    My spirits were that high, or higher. I'd come so far, climbed so 
    high... surely the last 1500 feet to the top of the world could be
    no worse than the distance I'd already climbed. Conditions were 
    good, and I was calm, looking forward a bit starry-eyed to the 
    summit of Everest, now so near. 
    <p/>
    But nothing came naturally at this altitude... and communications 
    to Base Camp flowed more easily than between tents. Unbeknownst to
    me, and only a few yards away, one member of our summit team had 
    suffered a minor stroke. Another had an upper respiratory 
    disorder, destined to get worse. 
    <p/>
    Alex, in radio contact with Eric at Base Camp, agreed that these 
    two would have to descend immediately, with two of us to assist. 
    Alex and I were elected. 
    <p/>
    When I got the word I was going down, without the background 
    information, I hit the roof. (It was, after all, a small tent.) I 
    had worked hard for months to get to this place, the weather 
    seemed good, I felt strong. I needed to have somebody look me in 
    the eye and explain to me why my descent was suddenly necessary. 
    <p/>
    The person who got that job was Mike Rheinberger. I'd spent a lot 
    of time with Mike in the months leading up to this point. Outside 
    of climbing, we had a number of things in common. But for a person
    as well rounded as Mike, everyone could say that. 
    <p/>
    Mike said very little. He struggled a bit for words... said that 
    he knew the route well, and even with his experience, the route 
    ahead was at the "very limit of (his) ability"... shuffling a bit,
    he said he was more prepared, that his equipment was better than 
    mine, that he was prepared to bivouac... conditions were not good,
    that the other two needed my support. Minutes later, I was on the 
    way down the mountain. 
    <p/>
    Mike (from Australia), Mark (from New Zealand) and Dave (from 
    Alaska) proceeded up the mountain the following morning. Rising 
    around midnight to begin the arduous process of preparing for the 
    ascent, eating, and melting enough snow to provide several litre's
    water apiece, they were underway by 4AM. 
    <p/>
    Dave, who had been my tentmate at Camp 6, had a timetable in mind.
    If he did not reach certain points by certain times, he would turn
    back. He did not trust his judgement with the summit so close. 
    Decide ahead of time; stick to it. I'd had a similar discussion 
    with Mike the day before. We talked of the "Everest Effect", 
    causing people to stretch their better judgement just because... 
    well, 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$cuz">Because It's There.</a>
    Remember Norman? 
    <a href="teacher?query=$$norman">Norman?</a>
    <p/>
    Dave turned around partway up the ridge. It was a good thing; he 
    was wasted, and had a tough descent. But as he descended, he 
    passed Mike and Mark, still ascending, even more slowly. 
    <p/>
    <img src="evm009.jpg" align="right"/>
    You could hardly ask for a more experienced team. Mark, a New 
    Zealand/Maori, seemed to carry with him aura of boundless 
    competence, confidence, and good humour; you could not help but 
    feel it anytime Mark was around. Among his many mountaineering 
    accomplishments, he'd climbed Everest once before from the North, 
    in 1991. Mike, a quiet and perceptive Australian, had been on 
    seven Everest expeditions, on both the Tibet side and the Nepal 
    side... and had been thwarted each time. 
    <p/>
    Mike, it seemed, had decided that this was it. Several times, Mark
    implored Mike to turn back. Mike was moving slowly, but he was 
    only moving upward. 
    <p/>
    Dave's deadline for the summit, if I remember right, was noon. 
    Norman got there at 3PM, and died during descent. Mike and Mark 
    got there at 7PM, just as the sun was going down. 
    <p/>
    Mark remembers it as being a most remarkable event... the clouds 
    below, the colour of sunset... the spectacle of Mike finally 
    reaching the summit, after so many years, so many attempts, so 
    many hardships and so many disappointments... Mike fell to the 
    ground and kissed the summit of Everest. 
    <p/>
    The glory was short-lived. They set about digging in for the 
    highest bivouac in the history of Man, 20 metres below the summit 
    of Everest. Various body parts froze. Oxygen ran out. Water and 
    food were gone. 
    <p/>
    On May 27, they made their way down the hill. Mike developed pain 
    in the upper legs, probably blood clots. If they broke up and 
    reached the heart, it would be instantly fatal. Moving was the 
    worst thing he could do. It was also the only thing he could do to
    survive. 
    <p/>
    Mike became delirious. Mark's feet and parts of his hands froze. 
    There is a snowfield where we could see them quite clearly from 
    Camp III, where I was at that point. We cheered as they crossed 
    it, suddenly surging forward; and our spirits surged with them. 
    <p/>
    But Mike's eyes developed retinal hemorrages. He was blind, 
    dehydrated, delirious, exhausted, the highest person in the world 
    and a long way from home. The day wore on. They were hardly 
    moving. 
    <p/>
    The next summit team, ascending from Camp 6, became a rescue 
    mission. Several people saw that their long journey, and their 
    months of effort, were not destined to culminate in the summit of 
    Everest; instead, they'd culminate in the placing of an oxygen 
    bottle which, with luck, Mike and Mark might reach... 
    <p/>
    As the sun set on the 27th, Mike and Mark were between the 1st and
    2nd Steps. Mark descended to get a bottle of oxygen stashed at the
    top of the 1st Step. When he got there, there was a long radio 
    conversation in an attempt to get Mark to descend alone. I don't 
    want to talk about this a whole lot. It was pretty apparent that 
    the best result one could hope for would be to get Mark back 
    alive. At one point, Eric said on the radio, "Mark, I don't want 
    to be the one to tell your wife..." About this time, Mike Perry, 
    Mark's longtime friend and fellow New Zealander, arrived in Base 
    Camp. He got on the radio, and with admirable (decisive?) 
    firmness, said... "Mark... <I>come down... NOW...</I>" 
    <p/>
    In the end, Mark was coaxed further down the hill. Jason, from the
    next team, met him below the 1st step. Without Mike, the two 
    climbers descended from the 1st Step to the relative comforts of 
    Camp 6. 
    <p/>
    <a href="teacher?query=$$rhein">Goodbye, Mike.</a>
    <p/>
    The next morning, Mike was spotted some 500 feet below the route. 
    I will guess that happened soon after Mark left for the oxygen... 
    before any of the above conversations. There is no question in my 
    mind that Mark's descent was the right thing for him to do. There 
    is also no question in my mind that Mark will relive that evening,
    in his mind, many, many times, wondering... 
  </answer>
</book>
